<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE faqs SYSTEM "faqs.dtd">
<faqs title="Exult" changed="03 Septembre 2001(GMT)">
	<section title="Changes to the FAQ">
		<faq name="03092001">
			<question>- 03 Septembre 2001</question>
			<answer>
				<ul>
				<li><ref1 target="latest_version"/> Version updated</li>
				<li><ref1 target="other_improvements"/> Added "close on doubleclick".</li>
				<li><ref1 target="known_issues"/> added note about stealing, killing NPCs</li>
				<li><ref1 target="compile_issues"/> added this with information on compiling in 
					Unix and the bug with the flex bundled with some Linux systems.</li>
				</ul>	
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="10082001">
			<question>- 10 August 2001</question>
			<answer>
				<ul>
				<li><ref1 target="origin_exult"/> noted praise from LB and Ken Demarest.</li>				
				<li><ref1 target="multiplayer"/> this gets asked quite often.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="whatis_snapshot"/> added some more information.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="compile_snapshot"/> made this gnereic for all the OS'.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="what_platforms"/> added OSX.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="addon_support"/> reported both as bug-free.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="other_improvements"/> added the status bars.</li>				
				<li><ref1 target="bug_report"/> not that anyone reads the FAQ anyway. But it should get
					 all the alpha testers on the right track.</li>
				</ul>	
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="19072001">
			<question>- 19 July 2001</question>
			<answer>
				<ul>
				<li>With the updated Documentation parts of the FAQ are no longer 
					necessary and thus left out. So see the <extref target="docs.php">Documentation</extref>
					for all your configuration problems</li>
				</ul>	
			</answer>
		</faq>
	</section>
	<section title="Introduction">
		<faq name="why_name_exult">
			<question>Why is it called <Exult/> - what is the meaning of this name?</question>
			<answer>
				<cite name="Jeff wrote on the Boards">
					I originally wrote it [Exult] solely for X-windows, so that's where
					the 'X' comes from. The "ult", of course, comes from Ultima. It
					was only about 6 months ago [02/29/2000] that I replaced the X code with SDL,
					which is multiplatform. Then Arthuris ported it to Win32 (and to
					BeOS). He had also ported the earlier version, but it was much harder
					to maintain that way.
				</cite>
				<cite name="Ibrahim Holtzmann">
					I'd like to point out that "exult" is also an English verb that
					means "to rejoice, to exhibit great happiness".
				</cite>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="is_exult_free">
			<question>Is <Exult/> free ?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					<Exult/> is more than free: it's Free (notice the caps). <Exult/> is released
					under the GNU GPL (General Public License). This means that the source code
					for <Exult/> is freely available and you can do whatever you want with it.
					However, if you make modifications to any of <Exult/>'s components and publicly
					redistribute your work you are required to make the source freely available
					in turn. Obviously the <Exult/> team would be very grateful if any
					modifications you make are contributed back to the main code, so that
					everyone can benefit from them. If you want to work on <Exult/> just send an
					e-mail to the 
					<extref target="mailto:exult-general@lists.sourceforge.net">team</extref>.<br/>
 					More information on the GNU GPL at 
 					<extref target="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html"/>.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="origin_exult">
			<question>Does Origin support <Exult/>?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					First of all, Origin has been owned by EA for a long time now and from recent 
					developements it seems that Origin only exists now to maintain Ultima Online. 
					Furthermore, Origin and/or people that worked for Origin claim that the source 
					code for Ultima 7 (BG/SI) has been lost for some time.
					So there is no chance for the <Exult/> team to have a look at the actual code.
				</para>
				<para>
					Also the team tried to contact some people from Origin earlier but got no positive
					or negative response on the <Exult/> project. So far it seems that both Origin and 
					EA have decided to ignore <Exult/>.
				</para>
				<para>
					On the other hand former Origin employees contacted the team and congratulated the 
					team on their effort. Most noticeable are Lord British himself and Ken Demarest 
					(Programming Manager of Ultima 7)(hint:spell his name backwards).
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="other_ultimas">
			<question>Will <Exult/> support other Ultimas?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					<Exult/> supports only Ultima 7 (BG/SI and the add-ons). It will never support
					any other Ultima nor do members of the team plan to develop something similar.
					The reasons for this are that no other Ultima is similar to Ultima 7 in the 
					internal workings and also the team is quite sick of reverse engineering a game
					allready. 
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="multiplayer">
			<question>Will there be a multiplayer <Exult/>?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					No.
				</para>
				<cite name="Jeff on the Forum">
					The question is 'why?'. I continue working on <Exult/>, in large part, because 
					nobody makes games like Ultima7 anymore. While I think a multi-player game 
					would be technically interesting, I don't see the need. There are <em>lots</em> 
					of them already, and many experienced people working on new ones.
				</cite>
				<para>
					Note however that <Exult/> is open source. If you want a multiplayer U7 no one
					holds you back to code it in. 
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="whereis_exult">
			<question>Where do I find <Exult/>?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					The latest official version is found on <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/"/><br/>
					Daily snapshots of the Win32 binary and of the CVS source tree can be found at
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/download.php"/>
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="whatis_snapshot">
			<question>What is a snapshot? Are these screenshots or what?</question>
			<answer>
			    <para>
			    	Bugs and not yet implemented features in <Exult/> get fixed almost daily in the code.
			    	A release is very time consuming that's why there are so few.
			    </para>	
			    <para>
					The snapshot is the newest source code of the program. It is updated almost
					daily, sometimes twice a day. There is information on how to build your
					own binary in the source but there is also the newest pre-compiled Windows binary.
					If you there is no new one this means that either there were no changes to the code
					or the source failed to compile.
				</para>
				<para>
					Also this FAQ mainly addresses the snapshots as people use them and ask question.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="compile_snapshot">
			<question>How do I compile a source code snapshot for my OS?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					The source code snapshots contain a file called "README.OS" (like Readme.win32, 
					Readme.MacOS) that explains everything.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="latest_version">
			<question>What is the latest version of <Exult/>?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					The current official release is V0.94 Alpha5. See also <ref target="whereis_exult"/>
					to learn where to get the latest version.
				</para>
				<para>
					To find out which version you are running, press <key>v</key> while in game.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="what_platforms">
			<question>On what platform does <Exult/> run?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					<Exult/> should be able to be compiled (with minor modifications) on
					any platform that SDL supports. Right now the source can be compiled
					in Linux/i386, Linux/Alpha, MacOS, OSX, OpenBSD, FreeBSD, Solaris, BeOS and 
					Win32 (Windows 9x/ME/NT/2000).
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
	</section>
  	<section title="Exult and Ultima 7">
		<faq name="u7_needed">
			<question>Do I need Ultima 7?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					Yes. <Exult/> won't work without the original files.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="u7_versions">
			<question>Does <Exult/> work on all versions of the game?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					It seems to run most of the available versions of the game. The most common
					ones nowadays with the included Add-Ons (Forge of Virtue and Silver Seed) 
					runs for sure.
				</para>
				<para>
					However there are reported problems with the localized versions of the
					game (French, German and Spanish). Conversation threads don't seem to skip to the
					next line in the proper places and therefore are unreadable in some cases. SI
					was only published in English so no localization problems with that one.
				</para>
				<para>
					V0.91 Alpha2 adds fixes for the french version, which should work now.
					No work has been done for the german version, due to lack of testers. If
					you have the German or Spanish version, and want it to run, contact us.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="si_support">
			<question>How about Serpent Isle?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					The team is working on it. It is not yet fully playable but you can walk around,
					talk to people, finish a lot of quests... Plotwise you will
					get quite far but you certainly won't be able to play through it yet.
				</para>
				<para>
					Old quotes on this topic from the time when SI wasn't playable at all in <Exult/>.
				</para>
				<cite name="Colourless">
					I can't say much about the what will happen except that a completely
					working Serpent Isle will be an annoying task to complete. It is
					close to BG in some ways, but very different in others. 
				</cite>
				<cite name="Jeff">
					My feelings about SI are the same as Colourless, who has done all
					the work so far on it. I'd much prefer to add enhancements to BG
					(which would apply to SI as well), and perhaps write a new RPG.
					Now, if EA would provide us with information about SI's internals,
					that would change things. And also, since Exult is open-source,
					it would be fine if anyone wants to volunteer to work on SI.
				</cite>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="addon_support">
			<question>Do the Add-Ons work?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					"Forge of Virtue" (Add-On to Black Gate) and the "The Silver Seed" 
					(Add-On to Serpent Isle) are bug-free now.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="play_through_u7">
			<question>Can you play through U7 yet?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					You can play through the Black Gate/Forge of Virtue without cheating and
					plotholes.<br/>
					SI is partially playable since V0.91 Alpha2.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="old_savegames">
			<question>Do savegames from the original work in <Exult/>?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					Savegames that were made with the original Ultima 7 or U7Run don't work
					with <Exult/>. You have to start a new game when you begin playing with <Exult/>.
					Sorry! 
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="u7_download">
			<question>Where do I find Ultima 7 on the net to download?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					<em>Don't!</em> You may be able to find it on the net but it would be
					pirating the game and the <Exult/> team doesn't support pirates. Look for
					the Ultima Collection in stores or on Ebay (<extref target="http://www.ebay.com"/>).
				</para>
				<para>
					<em>Don't</em> ask the team for copies.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
	</section>
 	<section title="Miscellaneous">
		<faq name="cheat_rooms_work">
			<question>Do the various cheat rooms work?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					Yes.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="where_cheat_rooms">
			<question>Where Do I find them</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					Just keep on looking for them :-)
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="transports_work">
			<question>Do the carriages, ships and the magic carpet work?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					Yes. The sail of ships look odd sometimes but otherwise these means of
					transportations work quite well.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="party_formation">
			<question>Why is the party formation different?</question>
			<answer>				
				<para>
					In <Exult/> the party (the Avatar and his companions) move quite differently than
					they do in the original. This is actually not a bug but a disliking of the old
					style.
				</para>
				<cite name="Jeff">
					It's not a bug, it's a feature! I like it that way.  Everyone is sensitive to 
					different things, and I always though the formation-walking in the original 
					U7 looked really stupid. Eventually, someone may add the original type of walking 
					to Exult, probably as an option.
				</cite>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="bg_improvements">
			<question>
				Serpent Isle had many more improvements over Black Gate (keyring,
				better paperdoll...). Will these be implemented?
			</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					Right now the main goal is to get the Black Gate 100% working. After
					that it could be that some more things will be improved as far as it
					is possible to implement these.
				</para>
				<para>
					The keyring is not in Black Gate but there is the <key>k</key> key
					which tries all the keys in the inventory to open a lock.
				</para>
				<para>
					Recently Ryan added paperdoll support in Black Gate. Though it is
					still buggy (some items disappear to Neverneverland) it is beautiful
					to look at. Very impressive. For this you need to have Serpent Isle
					installed on your hard drive and you must set the path to it in exult.cfg
					(see the <extref target="docs.php">Documentation</extref>). If an item 
					seems to have disappeared press <key>F2</key> to activate the cheat menu 
					and disable Paperdolls. Now you should find that missing item in your inventory. 
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="other_improvements">
			<question>Any other improvements/features?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					You can now close gumps with a double click like it worked in Ultima8. See 
					"Configurations" in the Documentation.
				</para>
				<para>
					Since the Alpha 4 release a new game menu was added with improved Audio and Video 
					Options boxes (the Gameplay Options don't work yet) and a very much improved 
					(<strong>awesome</strong>)savegame box. This allows you much more savegames than 
					the original (you should run out of disc space before you run out of savegame slots), 
					shows a screenshot of the location you saved at, the members of your party, your stats,
					game time and the date you actually saved. The game menu is opened via <key>Esc</key> 
					and the save game box is opened either via the game menu or the <key>s</key> key.
				</para>
				<para>
					Post Alpha 4 the team added status bars to the game. Press <key>r</key> while playing 
					to see it.
				</para>
				<para>
					In <Exult/>, you can still move your party even if there is a box/body/stats
					open/on. In the original, the world was kind of frozen. Now it is only
					frozen if you hit the <key>t</key> or <key>s</key> key.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="disable_improvements">
			<question>
				How do I disable all improvements?
			</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					To get an Ultima 7 that looks and behaves as close to the original as possible there
					are several things to do (though I wonder why you'd want to do that):
				</para>
				<ul>
				<li>make custom keybindings files (see <extref target="docs.php">Documentation</extref>) 
					in which you disable all the keys that were not in the original for Black Gate and 
					Serpents Isle.<br/> 
					Since the Alpha 4 release you have to assign <key>s</key> to old_file_gump
					to enable the old savegame menu (the line in your custom keybindings file should look 
					like: S old_file_gump)</li>
				<li>Edit the exult.cfg file to point to those custom keys.</li>
				<li>Don't set the path to the Serpent Isle files (see <extref target="docs.php">Documentation</extref>)
					 and put SI and a second copy of <Exult/> in a seperate directory (note: you can no longer 
					launch both BG and SI from the same exult.exe). This disables SI paperdolls in BG.</li>
				<li>Alternatively you can leave the cheat menu binding in the keybindings file (<key>F2</key>) 
					and disable "Paperdolls" each time you run <Exult/>.</li>
				<li>Edit the exult.cfg to use the resolution of 320x200, to run in full screen and 
					disable scalers.</li>
				<li>The disc icon in the Avatar paperdoll opens the new game menu. As of now this cannot 
					be altered. Sorry!</li> 
				</ul>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="exult_engine">
			<question>
				I heard that <Exult/> is meant to be a game engine. Can I make my own game with <Exult/>?
			</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					Work has begun on "<Studio/>" which is aimed to be an editor for
					all kinds of files that are used by Ultima 7. As of now there is already
					a <extref target="http://www.gimp.org/">Gimp</extref> plug-in to edit shapes.
				</para>
				<para>
					For much more information "<Studio/>" see <ref2 target="Exult Studio"/>.
				</para>
				<cite name="Jeff">
					As for the future, my main plan is to add editing capabilities,
					with the long-range goal of writing an original RPG.
				</cite>
			</answer>
		</faq>
	</section>
	<section title="Exult Studio">
		<faq name="what_is_studio">
			<question>What is it?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					<Studio/> is a map-editor for <Exult/>, allowing you to modify the map of a 
					game and, eventually, to create a completely new landscape for a new game.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="cool_name">
			<question>Who came up with the cool name?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					Tristan
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="need_to_run">
			<question>What do you need to run it?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					Currently, you need to be running <Exult/> on X (Linux, Unix, etc.), with
					<Exult/> set to run in a window (not fullscreen).  You also need the GTK+
					library installed.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="port_platforms">
			<question>When will it be ported to other platforms?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					That depends on when someone volunteers to do the work :-) There are
					three issues:
				</para>
				<ul>
   				<li>GTK has to be ported to the platform. I think this is already
					true for Win32.</li>
   				<li><Studio/> uses sockets to communicate with <Exult/>.  This also 
					shouldn't be a problem for Win32.</li>
   				<li>X drag-n-drop is used to put new objects on the landscape.  The
					'drop' part of this will have to be rewritten for Win32 <Exult/>, OR,
					drag-n-drop could be an enhancement to SDL someday.</li>
				</ul>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="how_to_run">
			<question>How do you run it?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					You can run <Studio/> all by itself, but it isn't useful that way,
					as it uses <Exult/> as a server.  What you really want to do is:
				</para>
				<ul>
   				<li>Put 'exult_studio.glade' in the <Exult/> 'data' directory.</li>
   				<li>Be sure 'exult_studio' is in your path.</li>
   				<li>Run <Exult/>.</li>
   				<li>Press 'alt-ctrl-m' to go into 'map-editor' mode.  If all is set
					up correctly, exult_studio will start up, and will have a list of files
					on the left side of its window.</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					You can also start up one or the other separately, and they'll
					reconnect:
				</para>
				<ul>
    			<li>If <Exult/> isn't running, start it up.  Then, in <Studio/>,
					use the 'File' menu to choose the static directory (for the game you're
					playing).</li>
   				<li>If <Studio/> isn't running start it up with:
        			exult_studio -x (path to dir containing exult_studio.glade) -d 
        			(path to game directory)</li>
				</ul>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="what_can_do_at_moment">
			<question>What can you do at the moment?</question>
			<answer>
				<ul>
				<li>You can browse shapes in the main window.</li>
   				<li>You can drag a shape from the shape browser to <Exult/>, and that
					object will be placed in the game.  (Note:  Not all such objects 
					are saved with the game yet; saving things like buildings will be 
					implemented soon.)</li>
   				<li>You can edit an 'egg' by double-clicking on it.  An edit box
					should appear.</li>
   				<li>You can create a new 'egg' using the pull-down menu in <Studio/>.  
					In the Egg edit box, after you hit 'Apply', you'll be prompted to
					click in <Exult/> where you want the egg to appear.</li>
   				<li>If editing a 'monster' egg, you can set the monster by dragging
					the shape from the browser to the area that displays the monster.</li>
				</ul>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="what_next">
			<question>What's next?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					The next things to be implemented are:
				</para>
				<ul>
    			<li>An NPC editor, similar to the one for Eggs (but with lots more
					stuff to set).</li>
   				<li>A simple object editor, that lets you modify an object's
					'quality', 'quantity' and flags.</li>
   				<li>A 'save-map' function in <Exult/> to save the whole map (not just
					the moveable objects that 'save-game' stores).</li>
				</ul>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="client_server_stuff">
			<question>What's with this client/server stuff?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					A map-editor needs to provide the ability to display the game, place
					objects on the map, and move objects around.  That functionality is already in
					<Exult/>, and it makes sense to reuse it.  So we could have made <Exult/> a part of
					<Studio/>.  However, <Exult/> is already a huge program, and is getting
					unwieldy to work on.
				</para>
				<para>  
					With this architecture, <Studio/> can have all the messy code for 
					displaying/editing dialog boxes, while <Exult/> only needs a little bit
					of work to handle requests.
				</para>
				<para>
					Also, I (Jeff) wanted to get a little experience programming with
					sockets:-)
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
	</section>
  	<section title="Bugs, known issues and not yet implemented features">
		<faq name="known_bugs">
			<question>Bugs</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					To see a list of open bugs and bugreports go to
					<extref target="http://sourceforge.net/bugs/?group_id=2335"/>
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="bug_report">
			<question>How do I submit a proper bug report?</question>
			<answer>
				<ol>
				<li>Read the <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/docs.php">Documentation</extref>
					and this FAQ to see if that is not allready covered and you have all set up correctly.</li>
				<li>Before you report a bug to the 
					<extref target="http://sourceforge.net/bugs/?group_id=2335">bug tracker</extref> 
					please try the latest <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/download.php">snapshot</extref>.
					If the bug still occurs make sure that no one else allready reported the bug.</li>
				<li>If you are not a sourceforge member please include your e-mail address this is 
					important so we can get back to you. If you are a sourceforge member please log in 
					before submitting a bug.</li>
				<li>Make sense in the topic! For example, if the problem is with Rowenna in Skara Brae 
					don't just choose "Skara Brae" in the topic. "BG: Rowenna crashes game" makes more 
					sense. Sadly the space for the topics is limited. Explain the topic in "Detailed 
					Description".</li>
				<li>State which Operating System you use (Windows 9X, Linux, ...).</li>
				<li>Please include a savegame (use common sense if it is really needed). You will find 
					those in the game directories you put in the exult.cfg. They are called exult**bg.sav 
					(** is a number) for BG and exult**si.sav for SI. Zip it (important as Sourceforge 
					seems to have a size limit). As some parts of the game may require you to complete 
					other quests or stuff before you get to the bug you want to report it's much easier 
					for the team to look at the problem (speeds the process up a bit as they are much more 
					likely you take a look at the problem this way).</li>
				</ol>
				<para>
					So if you want to have a bug fixed follow these steps!
				</para>	
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="known_issues">
			<question>Known Issues</question>
			<answer>
				<ul>
					<li>Stealing and killing innocent NPCs doesn't work yet like it does in the original</li>
					<li>Movement is sometimes jerky or slow.</li>
					<li>We don't know what all the data in 'weapons.dat' and 'ammo.dat'
						means, so hit points and damage don't work as well as in the original
						game.</li>
					<li>Sound effects in SI are sometimes odd with the wave pack as some 
						sounds were coded in <Exult/> to correspond to the sfx number in BG. This 
						is a bug and will be addressed in due time.</li>
					<li>In Fellowship meetings some NPCs appear not to attend these though
						they should and sometimes even speak there. This is due to a bug in <Exult/> 
						which makes NPCs sit on already taken seats and only the top most NPC can 
						be seen. Moving the top most via Hackmover makes the others visible.</li>
					<li>If you run a resolution higher than the original (320x200) some NPCs
						that are further away from the Avatar may seem to disappear and reappear when
						you get away or closer to them.</li>
					<li>With scalers enabled you might encounter slow downs of the game. The team is
						working on this right now and it is already a lot faster.</li>
					<li>The speech in the intro is out of synch with the lips animations. But now it 
						matches the speed of the text.</li>
					<li>There are reported problems with digital sound effects or speech when 
						using Vortex series sound cards (like the Diamond MX 300) under Win9x/ME. <Exult/>
						is triggering a bug in the drivers. No workaround for now.</li>
				</ul>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="compile_issues">
			<question>Known Compile Issues</question>
			<answer>
				<ul>
					<li>Max is working to make Exult compile on all Unix systems but currently it requires
						SDL 1.2.3. When that works there will be compile instructions in the source.</li>
					<li>There is a bug/incompatibility with the flex bundled Linux distributions 
						(RH7.0, for example) that breaks compilation. Upgrading to a more recent version 
						of flex should fix it.</li>
				</ul>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="not_yet_implemented">
			<question>Not yet implemented</question>
			<answer>
				<ul>
					<li>A few magic spells don't work yet.</li>
					<li>stealing, killing innocent NPCs doesn't work yet</li>
				</ul>				
			</answer>
		</faq>
	</section>
	<section title="Questions and Answers">
		<faq name="howto_get_answers">
			<question>
				How can I get answers concerning Ultima 7/<Exult/>?
			</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					The best way to get answers to questions is to go to the Online discussion forum at:<br/>
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/forum/"/>
				</para>
				<para>
					To get answers concerning Ultima 7 in general go to the Ultima newsgroup:<br/>
					<extref target="news://rec.games.computer.ultima.series"/>
				</para>
				<para>
					Or go to the Ultima Dragons homepage <extref target="http://www.udic.org"/> and find your
					way from there (this is an online Ultima fanclub)
				</para>
				<para>
					Some <Exult/> developers like to hang out on IRC on irc.openprojects.net, channel #exult.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="contact">
			<question>How do I contact the author of this FAQ?</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					This FAQ is maintained by Dominus Dragon of the 
					<extref target="http://www.udic.org">UDIC</extref>
					aka <extref target="mailto:gigdr@tesionmail.de">Dominik Reichardt</extref>.
					Feel free to contact me with improvements or complaints regarding
					the FAQ. I recently became part of the <Exult/> Team though I only
					write the FAQ and don't code at all.
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
	</section>
	<section title="Links and Thanks">
		<faq name="main_links">
			<question>Important Links</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					<Exult/> homepage at <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/"/><br/>
					Daily code snapshot at <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/download.php"/><br/>
					Message board at <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/forum/"/><br/>
					Bugreports to <extref target="http://sourceforge.net/bugs/?group_id=2335"/>
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
		<faq name="thanks">
			<question>Thanks</question>
			<answer>
				<para>
					Of course big thanks go to the <Exult/> Team for breathing life back into
					this jewel of a game.
				</para>
				<para>
					Max Horn deserves my gratitude for making the FAQ easier to maintain via XML/XSL.
				</para>
				<para>
					Thanks to all those I stole comments from without quoting them, those
					that sent me improvements and don't get quoted and so on. If you helped
					me in some way feel my gratitude without being mentioned.
				</para>
				<para>
					Thanks go to <strong>Matt0</strong> who really got me thinking about doing 
					this FAQ (though he just did it to tease me).
				</para>
			</answer>
		</faq>
	</section>
</faqs>