<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE faqs SYSTEM "docs.dtd">
<faqs title="Exult" changed="24 October 2002(GMT)">
	<section title="Changes to the FAQ">
		<sub name="24102002">
			<header>- 24 October 2002</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
				<li><ref1 target="save_crash"/> Don't save on scripted scenes.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="skarabrae_sacrifice"/> Some people still run into this problem.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="by_design"/> walking style revisited.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="11092002">
			<header>- 11 September 2002</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
				<li><ref1 target="what_platforms"/> changed location of Zaurus package.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="party_formation"/> rewrote that a bit.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="great_hierophant"/> not an issue with Exult actually.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="24072002">
			<header>- 24 July 2002</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
				<li><ref1 target="what_platforms"/> the Amiga port has been integrated ages ago
					and we have a Zaurus port now.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="compile_issues"/> makefile.cygwin no longer exists.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="18062002">
			<header>- 18 June 2002</header>
			<body>
				<ul>				
				<li><ref1 target="different_snapshot"/> same as on our main page, also some explanation 
					for the different FAQ/Docs.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="studio_support"/> <Studio/> is no longer supported in RC2 and stable 
					snapshots.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="bug_report"/> SourceForge requires registration for attaching files.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Introduction">
		<sub name="why_name_exult">
			<header>Why is it called <Exult/> - what is the meaning of this name?</header>
			<body>
				<cite name="Jeff wrote on the Boards">
					I originally wrote it [Exult] solely for X-windows, so that's where
					the 'X' comes from. The "ult", of course, comes from Ultima. It
					was only about 6 months ago [02/29/2000] that I replaced the X code with SDL,
					which is multiplatform. Then Arthuris ported it to Win32 (and to
					BeOS). He had also ported the earlier version, but it was much harder
					to maintain that way.
				</cite>
				<cite name="Ibrahim Holtzmann">
					I'd like to point out that "exult" is also an English verb that
					means "to rejoice, to exhibit great happiness".
				</cite>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="is_exult_free">
			<header>Is <Exult/> free ?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<Exult/> is more than free: it's Free (notice the caps). <Exult/> is released
					under the GNU GPL (General Public License). This means that the source code
					for <Exult/> is freely available and you can do whatever you want with it.
					However, if you make modifications to any of <Exult/>'s components and publicly
					redistribute your work you are required to make the source freely available
					in turn. Obviously the <Exult/> team would be very grateful if any
					modifications you make are contributed back to the main code, so that
					everyone can benefit from them. If you want to work on <Exult/> just send an
					e-mail to the
					<extref target="mailto:exult-general@lists.sourceforge.net">team</extref>.<br/>
 					More information on the GNU GPL at
 					<extref target="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html"/>.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="origin_exult">
			<header>Does Origin support <Exult/>?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					First of all, Origin has been owned by EA for a long time now and from recent
					developments it seems that Origin only exists now to maintain Ultima Online.
					Furthermore, Origin and/or people that worked for Origin claim that the source
					code for Ultima 7 (BG/SI) has been lost for some time.
					So there is no chance for the <Exult/> team to have a look at the actual code.
				</para>
				<para>
					Also the team tried to contact some people from Origin earlier but got no positive
					or negative response on the <Exult/> project. So far it seems that both Origin and
					EA have decided to ignore <Exult/>.
				</para>
				<para>
					On the other hand former Origin employees contacted the team and congratulated the
					team on their effort. Most noticeable are Lord British himself and Ken Demarest
					(Programming Manager of Ultima 7)(hint:spell his name backwards).
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="other_ultimas">
			<header>Will <Exult/> support other Ultimas?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<Exult/> supports only Ultima 7 (BG/SI and the add-ons). It will never support
					any other Ultima nor do members of the team plan to develop something similar.
					The reasons for this are that no other Ultima is similar to Ultima 7 in the
					internal workings and also the team used to be quite sick of reverse engineering
					a game already.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="pentagram">
			<header>But isn't <Pentagram/> some kind of <Exult/> for U8?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<Pentagram/> is a pet project by some members of the <Exult/> team (currently mostly
					Willem, Colourless, Fingolfin and Darke). It is a <strong>map and shapes viewer</strong>
					and nothing more (although the team does indeed invest some time to disassemble the Usecode
					of U8). It isn't meant to be something similar to <Exult/>. It is rather a clever plan
					to stir up interest in other coders to carry this basic work further.<br/>
					Any <strong>developer</strong> is welcome to take a look and contact us.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="multiplayer">
			<header>Will there be a multiplayer <Exult/>?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					No.
				</para>
				<cite name="Jeff on the Forum">
					The question is 'why?'. I continue working on <Exult/>, in large part, because
					nobody makes games like Ultima7 anymore. While I think a multiplayer game
					would be technically interesting, I don't see the need. There are <em>lots</em>
					of them already, and many experienced people working on new ones.
				</cite>
				<para>
					Note however that <Exult/> is open source. If you want a multiplayer U7 no one
					holds you back to code it in.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="whereis_exult">
			<header>Where do I find <Exult/>?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The latest official version is found on 
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/"/><br/>
					Daily snapshots (by Travis Howell) of the Win32 binary and of the CVS source tree 
					can be found at
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/download.php"/>.<br/>
					A BeOS binary snapshot can be found at
					<extref target="http://digilander.iol.it/burton666/exult-beos.zip"/>. Jack Burton 
					provides this weekly or whenever it compiles for him. Thanks!<br/>
					There is also a version available for AmigaOS/MorphOS at
					<extref target="http://www.muenster.de/~tomjoad/exult.html"/>. Please see
					<ref target="what_platforms"/> for some more information on this port.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="whatis_snapshot">
			<header>What is a snapshot? Are these screenshots or what?</header>
			<body>
			    <para>
			    	Bugs and not yet implemented features in <Exult/> get fixed almost daily in the code.
			    	A release is very time consuming that's why there are so few.
			    </para>
			    <para>
					The snapshot is the newest source code of the program. It is updated almost
					daily, sometimes twice a day. There is information on how to build your
					own binary in the source but there is also the newest pre-compiled Windows executable.
					If you there is no new one this means that either there were no changes to the code
					or the source failed to compile.
				</para>
				<para>
					Also this FAQ mainly addresses the snapshots as people use them and ask question.
					And all the new features and improvements are found in those!
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="different_snapshot">
			<header>Why are there now two different snapshots?</header>
			<body>
			    <para>
			    	If you checked our download page recently, you may have noticed that we have 
			    	two sets of development snapshots now: a 1.0.x (stable) snapshot, and a 
			    	1.1.x (unstable) snapshot.
			    </para>
			    <para>
					The 1.0.x branch will become our 1.0 release soon, hopefully, and we will mainly 
					be fixing any remaining bugs in this branch. We recommend using the 1.0.x 
					snapshots for playing and testing Exult. 
				</para>
				<para>
					The 1.1.x branch is meant mostly as a 'developer playground' at the moment. 
					We are making some very destabilizing changes to this branch, like a rewritten 
					usecode interpreter and new audio code. We do not recommend using the 1.1.x 
					snapshots for normal playing.
				</para>
				<para>
			    	This also means that the documentation and the FAQ needs to be different. You will
			    	find the description of the 1.1.x branch features only in the snapshot and the source
			    	and not on our homepage.
			    </para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="compile_snapshot">
			<header>How do I compile a source code snapshot for my OS?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The source code snapshots contain a file called "README.OS" (like Readme.win32,
					Readme.MacOS) that explains everything.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="latest_version">
			<header>What is the latest version of <Exult/>?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The current official release is V0.99.1 RC 2 (Release Candidate 2).
					See also <ref target="whereis_exult"/>
					to learn where to get the latest version.
				</para>
				<para>
					To find out which version you are running, press <key>v</key> while in game.
				</para>
				<para>
					And if you are wondering about our strange version numbering, we can't help you as 
					we have no clue about it as well.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="what_platforms">
			<header>On what platform does <Exult/> run?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<Exult/> should be able to be compiled (with minor modifications) on
					any platform that SDL supports. Right now the source can be compiled
					in Linux/i386, Linux/Alpha, MacOS (requires at least MacOS 8.5 or higher), 
					OSX, OpenBSD, FreeBSD, Solaris, BeOS and Win32 (Windows 9x/ME/NT4/2000/XP).
				</para>
				<para>
					Ruediger Hanke's ported <Exult/> to MorphOS and AmigaOS. You can get this 
					version at <extref target="http://www.muenster.de/~tomjoad/exult.html"/>.
				 </para>
				 <para>
					Recently Artaxerxes started working on a port for 
					<extref target="http://www.myzaurus.com/">Zaurus</extref>, a Linux/ARM based PDA.
					It is already fully playable (Artaxerxes played through SI). Pictures of the Zaurus 
					running SI can be found at 
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/images/screenshots/zaurus/"/> and an 
					IPK package at <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/download.php"/>.
				 </para>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
  	<section title="Exult and Ultima 7">
		<sub name="u7_needed">
			<header>Do I need Ultima 7?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Yes. <Exult/> won't work without the original files.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="u7_versions">
			<header>Does <Exult/> work on all versions of the game?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					It seems to run most of the available versions of the game. The most common
					ones nowadays with the included Add-ons (Forge of Virtue and Silver Seed)
					runs for sure.
				</para>
				<para>
					However there are reported problems with the localized versions of the
					game (French, German and Spanish). Conversation threads don't seem to skip to the
					next line in the proper places and therefore are unreadable in some cases. SI
					was published in English and Spanish (as we recently discovered to our surprise)
					but we seem to have fixed the main problem with the Spanish version.
				</para>
				<para>
					V0.91 Alpha2 adds fixes for the French version, which should work now.
					If you are running a Spanish or German version Black Gate and you notice
					problems please contact us.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="play_through_u7">
			<header>Can you play through U7 yet?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					You can play through the Black Gate/Forge of Virtue without cheating and
					plot holes.<br/>
					And since Beta1 the same is true for Serpent Isle/Silver Seed.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="si_support">
			<header>How about Serpent Isle?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Serpent Isle is now playable without cheating and plot holes. Two members of the team
					have already finished the game with <Exult/>.
				</para>
				<para>
					Old quotes on this topic from the time when SI wasn't playable at all in <Exult/>.
				</para>
				<cite name="Colourless">
					I can't say much about the what will happen except that a completely
					working Serpent Isle will be an annoying task to complete. It is
					close to BG in some ways, but very different in others.
				</cite>
				<cite name="Jeff">
					My feelings about SI are the same as Colourless, who has done all
					the work so far on it. I'd much prefer to add enhancements to BG
					(which would apply to SI as well), and perhaps write a new RPG.
					Now, if EA would provide us with information about SI's internals,
					that would change things. And also, since Exult is open-source,
					it would be fine if anyone wants to volunteer to work on SI.
				</cite>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="addon_support">
			<header>Do the Add-ons work?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					"Forge of Virtue" (Add-on to Black Gate) and the "The Silver Seed"
					(Add-on to Serpent Isle) are bug-free now.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="old_savegames">
			<header>Do save games from the original work in <Exult/>?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Save games that were made with the original Ultima 7 or U7Run don't work
					with <Exult/>. You have to start a new game when you begin playing with <Exult/>.
					Sorry!
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="u7_download">
			<header>Where do I find Ultima 7 on the net to download?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<em>Don't!</em> You may be able to find it on the net but it would be
					pirating the game and the <Exult/> team doesn't support pirates. Look for
					the Ultima Collection in stores or on EBay (<extref target="http://www.ebay.com"/>).
				</para>
				<para>
					<em>Don't</em> ask the team for copies. <em>Don't</em> ask on the forum for copies,
					your post and the entire thread <em>will</em> be deleted. And please don't ask for
					the answers to the copyright questions.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
 	<section title="Miscellaneous">
		<sub name="walkthroughs">
			<header>Where do I find a walkthrough?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					If you need help with the game itself, like walkthroughs, hints, location of
					NPCs items take a look at the following sites:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><extref target="http://members.aol.com/UltimaWrld/ultima07.html"/><br/>
						The Ultima 7 section of Excalibur's World of Ultima site.</li>
					<li><extref target="http://www.ultimainfo.net/Codex/Ultima7.htm"/><br/>
						Paulon Dragons selection of notes and information on Ultima 7.</li>
					<li><extref target="http://www.ultimainfo.net/Codex/FAQ2.htm#U7"/><br/>
						The Ultima 7 section of Paulon Dragons Ultima games FAQ.</li>
					<li><extref target="http://www.ultimainfo.net/FAQ/ultimafaqs.htm#11"/><br/>
						The U7 section of the more detailed Ultima Gameplay FAQ.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="arrow_walkning">
			<header>Why can't I move my party with the arrow keys?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					We haven't implemented this yet so you can only move the party with the mouse. 
					Nadir is aiming to implement it after the 1.0 release.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="transports_work">
			<header>Do the carriages, ships and the magic carpet work?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Yes. The sail of ships look odd sometimes but otherwise these means of
					transportation work quite well.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="how_move_ships">
			<header>So why can't I sail a ship in BG?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					To sail a ship in BG you naturally need to have the deed to this ship in your party.
					Then double-click on the sail of the ship and your party moves aboard it and sits down.
					Once they are all seated, double-click the gangplank to close it. Now double-click on 
					the sail once more to have it unfold. You should be able to move the ship then.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="si_ext_intro">
			<header>Will you implement the extended intro for SI?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The extended intro for Serpent Isle can be found at
					<extref target="http://www.io.com/~dloubet/"/>. At this moment we don't
					even think about implementing this extended intro.<br/>
					Why not?<br/>
					It sure would be nice to use it. But you may have noticed some effects
					missing from the intro. You may have noticed that there is no sound. You may
					have noticed that there is neither speech nor subtitles.<br/>
					All that would have to be addressed and add to that the longer running time and
					that you have to synchronize the music with it. Then what about the size of it?
					You would need to compress it and make sure all our supported platforms make use
					of it.
				</para>
				<para>
					Everyone volunteering to do it is welcome to.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>		
		<sub name="party_formation">
			<header>Why is the party formation different?</header>
			<body>				
				<para>
					In <Exult/> the party (the Avatar and his companions) move quite differently than
					they do in the original. The problem is that this was controlled by the original 
					executable. Changing the formation now is not as easy as it sounds as the party
					formation has effects on other game internals. Changing it to be more like the original
					may force us to replay the whole game to make sure we didn't introduce new bugs.
					Recently Jeff changed this a bit but it still is not the same as the original.
				</para>
				<cite name="Jeff">
					It's not a bug, it's a feature! I like it that way.  Everyone is sensitive to
					different things, and I always though the formation-walking in the original
					U7 looked really stupid. Eventually, someone may add the original type of walking
					to Exult, probably as an option.
				</cite>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="save_crash">
			<header>What should I do when Exult keeps crashing when I try to save?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					This is <strong>not</strong> normal behavior for Exult. Normally when you restart
					and "Journey Onward"  Exult will actually restore to the point you saved.
				</para>
				<para>
					<em>Please do not play further</em> at this point. You should restore to an earlier
					save game, no matter how much game time you loose. Your game must have gotten
					corrupted and when you play on with it you will most likely experience even more
					serious problems.
				</para>
				<para>
					Please also avoid saving when a scripted sequence is running. Whenever you can't control
					the Avatar on your own a scripted scene is running and saving at this time will break the 
					game on reloading.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="choppy_game">
			<header>Why does the game run so choppy?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Well, every Ultima required a fast computer. Even though <Exult/> is just an
					engine that runs the ancient Ultima 7 it still requires a fast computer.
				</para>
				<para>
					Seriously, if the game runs choppy for you, try the speed setting in the Game Options
					menu and if that doesn't help also play with the original resolution (320x200),
					try a different scaler or disable scaling altogether.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="no_sfx">
			<header>Why can't I hear the Sound Effects?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Please read the Audio section of our <extref doc="docs" target="wave_sfx"/>.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="linux_audio">
			<header>Why do I hear strange, noisy effects in Linux?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					This is due to a bug with OSS. We advice installing ALSA. Please read
					<extref doc="docs" target="linux_alsa"/> for a little more extensive
					explanation.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="diferent_volume">
			<header>Why is the music so much louder/softer than the sfx/speech?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Music is played via midi but the sfx (sound effects) and speech are
					played via wave. Midi and Wave volume are set up separately in the settings
					of your Operating System and not by <Exult/>.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="blank_screen">
			<header>Why does my monitor stay black when I try to run <Exult/>?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The most common reason for this is that you try to run Exult full screen in a
					resolution that isn't supported by either your monitor or your graphics card.
					Edit your exult.cfg (see <extref doc="docs" target="exult_config"/>) to disable
					full screen. If Exult now runs fine in a window you have to select a different 
					resolution (also editable in exult.cfg) to run it full screen.<br/>
					If it still doesn't run contact us.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="virtue_stones">
			<header>Why can't I cast mark/recall on the Virtue Runes?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					You never could do this in the original as well. You have to use the
					<strong>Virtue Stones</strong> that you find in the same building as the runes.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="skarabrae_sacrifice">
			<header>Why can't I get the scrifice in Skara Brae to work?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<em>SPOILER ALERT</em> 
				</para>
				<para>
					I'm trying to get Forsythe in Skara Brae to sacrifice himself to destroy the well of 
					souls. But I can't seem to get Rowenna or Trent to talk to me about sacrifice.<br/>
					The solution to this is that Rowenna and Trent are standing too far apart. When you 
					reunited the pair you initiated the conversation with Trent from too far away 
					(this happens when you run at a higher resolution than the original one).<br/>
					Now you can either reload a game from before you reunited them or you have to hackmove 
					Rowenna closer to Trent. After that the two will talk to you about sacrifice.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="pikeman_disappears">
			<header>Where is the pikeman that lets you train in Monitor (SI)?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The pikeman that lets you enter the list field in Monitor sometimes disappears due
					to a bug in the game (even the original).<br/>
					This bug occurs when you enter the banquet scene of Monitor. To avoid this bug, we 
					recommend, that you approach the banquet hall from the right and/or double-click the
					entrance door to the hall when the party is standing very close to it. 
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="great_hierophant">
			<header>Why can't I summon the Great Hierophant (SI)?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					If you follow some walkthrough you might find that your summoning of the
					Great Hierophant doesn't work. This is a problem with the walkthrough. You
					need to have a personal item of the Great Hierophant in your inventory, namely
					the Serpent Staff.
				</para>
				<para>
					If possible not just play following the walkthrough but go out and explore 
					Serpent Isle. It's hard to imagine someone could miss the cave to the east of 
					Monitor...
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="improvements">
			<header>
				What are the improvements in <Exult/> over the original Ultima 7?</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
				<li>Many more keyboard shortcuts than the original had. Including in BG the
					<key>k</key> key that checks if you have the right key for a lock in your
					inventory. The list of keys can be found in the Documentation.</li>
				<li>A new worked over Game Options menu. This menu is explained in detail in the
					<extref target="docs.php">Documentation</extref> and many of the following
					improvements  and Video/Audio options can be accessed via this menu. Open
					this Game Options Menu by pressing <key>Esc</key> in the game.</li>
				<li>SI style paperdoll (inventory screen) in BG. Very impressive. For this you
					need to have Serpent Isle installed on your hard drive and you must set the
					path to it in exult.cfg (see the Documentation) and activate it in the
					Gameplay Options<br/>.
					This new inventory screen acts sometimes a little buggy, so if an item seems
					to have disappeared disable the paperdolls in the Gameplay Options.</li>
				<li>A beautiful new save game box. This allows you much more save games than
					the original (you should run out of disc space before you run out of save game
					slots), shows a screenshot of the location you saved at, the members of your
					party, your stats, game time and the date you actually saved. The save game
					box is opened either via the game menu or the <key>s</key> key.</li>
				<li>Face status bars at the bottom of the screen that show your health (and that
					of your party members) as well as your mana. Double-clicking on the face opens
					the inventory and double-clicking on the bars shows the status screen.</li>
				<li>Middle mouse button support. In the normal game, the middle mouse button
					activates the target-function (which could also be accomplished by pressing
					't'). for modal gumps, the middle mouse acts as 'return', the right button
					as 'escape', so you can now for example accept the default slider value by
					just pressing the middle button. The escape function is also available
					during most other actions like selecting a target or conversations.</li>
				<li>Wheel mouse support. If you have a wheel mouse some features are auto-enabled
					in <Exult/>.<br/>
					In slider gumps (e.g. how much gold you want to
					drop), scrolling the mouse up/down, moves the slider either left or right.
					Holding down <key>Alt</key> while using the wheel scrolls 10 steps.<br/>
					The save game menu scrolls one line, while pressing <key>Alt</key> it scrolls
					pages.<br/>
					You can also scroll the map of the game up or down and while pressing
					<key>Alt</key>  you scroll left or right.</li>
				<li>Fast Mouse which makes the mouse cursor move faster in full screen mode.</li>
				<li>Multiracial Avatar in BG. As with the paperdoll support you need to have SI
					installed and the path set in exult.cfg.</li>
				<li>Higher resolutions than the original. You can set the resolution as high as
					your computer supports. But there are some issues with it and it is considered
					cheating.</li>
				<li>Compressed save games. Since Beta1 <Exult/> compresses save games by default as
					zip files. They are still labeled *.sav and have the save game name in the zip
					comment.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="paperdoll_issues">
			<header>
				Are there issues with the SI style paperdoll in BG?
			</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					There are some issues. The paperdoll in BG is still limited to the slots
					it had originally.<br/>
					That means:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li>You can either equip a pair of gauntlets or one/two rings.</li>
					<li>The 'shield behind back', 'weapon behind back' and 'belt' slots are one
					and the same in BG. (So if you have a weapon on your back, you can't use your
					belt slot)</li>
					<li>If an item seems to have disappeared disable the paperdolls in the Game
					Options, retrieve the item and enable the paperdolls again.</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					Sparks paperdoll looks very odd (Spark on steroids) as there is no paperdoll
					for kids in SI and we have to use the adult paperdoll. Unless someone draws
					heaps of art we can't do anything.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="disable_improvements">
			<header>
				How do I disable all improvements?
			</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					To get an Ultima 7 that looks and behaves as close to the original as possible there
					are several things to do (though I wonder why you'd want to do that):
				</para>
				<ul>
				<li>make custom key bindings files (see <extref target="docs.php">Documentation</extref>)
					in which you disable all the keys that were not in the original for Black Gate and
					Serpents Isle.<br/>
					Since the Alpha 4 release you have to assign <key>s</key> to old_file_gump
					to enable the old save game menu (the line in your custom key bindings file should look
					like: S old_file_gump)</li>
				<li>Edit the exult.cfg file to point to those custom keys.</li>
				<li>Disable SI-style paperdolls for BG in exult.cfg (see the documentation for that).</li>
				<li>Alternatively click on the disk icon and disable the paperdolls in the Gameplay
					Options.</li>
				<li>Edit the exult.cfg to use the resolution of 320x200, to run in full screen and
					disable scalers.</li>
				<li>The disc icon in the Avatar paperdoll opens the new game menu. As of now this cannot
					be altered. Sorry!</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="exult_engine">
			<header>
				I heard that <Exult/> is meant to be a game engine. Can I make my own game with <Exult/>?
			</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Work has begun on "<Studio/>" which is aimed to be an editor for
					all kinds of files that are used by Ultima 7. As of now there is already
					a <extref target="http://www.gimp.org/">Gimp</extref> plug-in to edit shapes.
				</para>
				<para>
					For much more information "<Studio/>" see <extref doc="studio" target="whatis_studio"/>.
				</para>
				<cite name="Jeff">
					As for the future, my main plan is to add editing capabilities,
					with the long-range goal of writing an original RPG.
				</cite>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="studio_support">
			<header>
				Why is <Studio/> not working with the RC2 or newer snapshots of <Exult/>?
			</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Please see <ref target="different_snapshot"/> for information on our two
					different branches. <Studio/> will no longer be supported in the 1.0.x (stable)
					branch. A lot of changes we will put into the unstable branch will directly
					concern <Studio/>.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
  	<section title="Bugs, known issues and not yet implemented features">
		<sub name="known_bugs">
			<header>Bugs</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					To see a list of open bugs and bug reports go to
					<extref target="http://sourceforge.net/bugs/?group_id=2335"/>
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="bug_report">
			<header>How do I submit a proper bug report?</header>
			<body>
				<ol>
				<li>Read the <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/docs.php">Documentation</extref>
					and this FAQ to see if that is not already covered and you have all set up correctly.</li>
				<li>Before you report a bug to the
					<extref target="http://sourceforge.net/bugs/?group_id=2335">bug tracker</extref>
					please try the latest
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/download.php">snapshot</extref>.
					If the bug still occurs make sure that no one else already reported the bug
					(in the bug tracker).</li>
				<li>If you are not a SourceForge member please include your e-mail address. This is
					important so we can get back to you. If you are a SourceForge member please log in
					before submitting a bug. If you are a member of SourceForge you will also get notified
					of follow ups on your bug automatically by E-mail.</li>
				<li>Make sense in the topic! For example, if the problem is with Rowenna in Skara Brae
					don't just choose "Skara Brae" in the topic. "BG: Rowenna crashes game" makes more
					sense. Sadly the space for the topics is limited. Explain the topic in "Detailed
					Description".</li>
				<li>Include information on what version of <Exult/> you are using. You should have used
					the latest snapshot but please tell us the date of the snapshot.</li>
				<li>State which Operating System you use (Windows 9X, Linux, ...).</li>
				<li>Please include a save game (use common sense if it is really needed). You will find
					those in the game directories you put in the exult.cfg. They are called exult**bg.sav
					(** is a number) for BG and exult**si.sav for SI. You can look up the filename in the
					save game dialog as well (to the right, above the party members). As some parts of the game
					may require you to complete other quests or stuff before you get to the bug you want to
					report it's much easier for the team to look at the problem (speeds the process up a bit
					as they are much more likely you take a look at the problem this way).<br/>
					<strong>You need to check the box saying "Check to upload and Attach file".</strong>.
					See this screenshot for an example:
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/images/sfbug.jpg"/></li>
				<li><em>One</em> bug per subject please.</li>
				</ol>
				<para>
					<strong>Note</strong> for attaching save games SourceForge requires users to be 
					registered. Therefore we strongly advice users to register with SF.<br/>
					Any bug report that requires a save game will most likely be 
					<strong>tagged invalid</strong> if we don't receive a save game after we requested it.
				</para>
				<para>
					You can also use our
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/forum/">forum</extref>
					to report bugs. But if you do please follow the guidelines mentioned above (you can't
					include a save game of course). Though be aware that bugs submitted to the bug tracker
					are more likely to get attention than bugs submitted to the forum.
				</para>
				<para>
					So if you want to have a bug fixed follow these steps!
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="by_design">
			<header>Broken by Design</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<Exult/> often behaves and works differently than the original Ultima 7. These
					behaviors are sometimes features that just differ from the way the original
					worked.<br/>
					Some are bugs that the development team consider to have almost no detrimental
					effect to the enjoyment/running of the game, but would require a large amount
					of time and effort to fix.<br/>
					Please don't bother the team about those as some of these will be fixed in the
					future, others will only be fixed when someone who thinks it should be done
					differently sits down and codes it.<br/>
					The following are such 'features' of Exult:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li>Birds and animals open doors and such, like the human and sentient
						creatures of Britannia do.</li>
					<li>Party members don't walk lockstep with the Avatar like they do in
						BG/SI. Please see <ref1 target="party_formation"/>.</li>
					<li>The way the Avatar and the companions walk. Is it 2 frames or 3 frames?
						This has been changed a lot as this was disputed almost every four weeks.
						Fianlly it works like the original and the Avatar uses two frames and the 
						companions use three frames.</li>
					<li>Combat works differently. We don't have any hard data or formulae
						that tell us how combat worked in BG/SI, so Dr.Code put something
						together. If you have any information you've worked out related to
						this, please tell either the forum or the exult-general mailing list.<br/>
						Recently Jeff added an option to change the combat difficulty in exult.cfg.
						See the <extref doc="docs" target="exult_config"/>.</li>
					<li>Negative health and unconsciousness. Yes, it may look weird to have
						people walking around with negative health, but that's the way it
						currently works.</li>
					<li>Some music loops endlessly in <Exult/>. This is actually a correction of a bug
						in the original. We respects the midi looping flag as set by U7's original data
						files but the original didn't. Users who prefer the original (broken) are able
						to choose so in the Game menu.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="known_issues">
			<header>Known Issues</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li>There might be a bug when you have any of the games installed in a 
						path with spaces in it (see <extref doc="docs" target="path_config"/>).</li>
					<li>Stealing and killing innocent NPCs doesn't work yet like it does in the original</li>
					<li>Movement is sometimes jerky or slow.</li>
					<li>We don't know what all the data in 'weapons.dat' and 'ammo.dat'
						means, so hit points and damage don't work as well as in the original
						game.</li>
					<li>If you run a resolution higher than the original (320x200) some NPCs
						that are further away from the Avatar may seem to disappear and reappear when
						you get away or closer to them.</li>
					<li>With scalers enabled you might encounter slow downs of the game. The team is
						working on this right now and it is already a lot faster.</li>
					<li>The speech in the intro is out of synch with the lips animation. But now it
						matches the speed of the text.</li>
					<li>There are reported problems with digital sound effects or speech when
						using Vortex series sound cards (like the Diamond MX 300) under Win9x/ME. <Exult/>
						is triggering a bug in the drivers.</li>
					<li>There is also a problem involving Win9x/ME, C-Media soundcard chipsets and MIDI music.
						We suggest you first upgrade your drivers to the newest ones. Get them at
						<extref target="http://www.cmedia.com.tw/"/>. If that doesn't help, please contact
						us.</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					Possible <strong>workaround</strong> for the above mentioned audio issues:<br/>
					We added a config file option for Windows "config/audio/force_waveout"
					that when set to "yes" will force SDL to use waveout rather than attempting to use
					DirectSound. Using this option may fix problems some people have with sound in
	  				Exult under Windows. Additionally it seems to fix the popping sound when starting
	  				Exult in Win9x/ME/2k.<br/>
	  				This setting is now the default setting so downloading the latest snapshot is the
	  				only thing you need to do.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="compile_issues">
			<header>Known Compile Issues</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li>There is a bug/incompatibility with the flex bundled Linux distributions
						(RH7.0, for example) that breaks compilation. Upgrading to a more recent version
						of flex should fix it.</li>
					<li>After compiling yourself remember to copy the exult*.flx files from the data dir in
						the source to the <Exult/> data dir you chose in exult.cfg. This applies only if
						you don't use "make install"</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="not_yet_implemented">
			<header>Not yet implemented</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li>Stealing, killing innocent NPCs doesn't work yet correctly</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Questions and Answers">
		<sub name="howto_get_answers">
			<header>
				How can I get answers concerning Ultima 7/<Exult/>?
			</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The best way to get answers to questions is to go to the Online discussion forum at:<br/>
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/forum/"/>
				</para>
				<para>
					To get answers concerning Ultima 7 in general go to the Ultima newsgroup:<br/>
					<extref target="news://rec.games.computer.ultima.series"/>
				</para>
				<para>
					Or go to the Ultima Dragons homepage <extref target="http://www.udic.org"/> and find your
					way from there (this is an online Ultima fan club)
				</para>
				<para>
					Some <Exult/> developers like to hang out on IRC on irc.openprojects.net, 
					channel #exult.<br/>
					The logs of #exult can be found at
					<extref target="http://www.math.leidenuniv.nl/~wpalenst/exultlog.php3"/>.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="contact">
			<header>How do I contact the author of this FAQ?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					This FAQ is maintained by Dominus Dragon of the
					<extref target="http://www.udic.org">UDIC</extref>
					AKA <extref target="mailto:gigdr@tesionmail.de">Dominik Reichardt</extref>.
					Feel free to contact me with improvements or complaints regarding
					the FAQ. I am part of the <Exult/> Team though I only
					write the FAQ and Documentation and don't code at all.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Links and Thanks">
		<sub name="main_links">
			<header>Important Links</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li><Exult/> homepage at <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/"/></li>
					<li>Daily code snapshot at <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/download.php"/></li>
					<li>Message board at <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/forum/"/></li>
					<li>Bug reports to <extref target="http://sourceforge.net/bugs/?group_id=2335"/></li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="thanks">
			<header>Thanks</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Of course big thanks go to the <Exult/> Team for breathing life back into
					this jewel of a game.
				</para>
				<para>
					Max Horn deserves my gratitude for making the FAQ easier to maintain via XML/XSL.
				</para>
				<para>
					Thanks to all those I stole comments from without quoting them, those
					that sent me improvements and don't get quoted and so on. If you helped
					me in some way feel my gratitude without being mentioned.
				</para>
				<para>
					Thanks go to <strong>Matt0</strong> who really got me thinking about doing
					this FAQ (though he just did it to tease me).
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
</faqs>