<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE studiodoc SYSTEM "docs.dtd">
<studiodoc title="Exult" changed="03 May 2002(GMT)">
	<section title="Changes to the Documentation">		
		<sub name="03052002">
			<header>03 May 2002</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					This is the second draft of the <Studio/> documentation. 					
				</para>
				<li><ref1 target="command_line"/> I had spaces between the commands and the options.</li>
				<li><section_ref target="Menu Options"/> description of all the Menu Options.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="can_do_atm"/> added warning on editing terrains.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="egg_edit"/> added place holder for actual documentation.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="npc_edit"/> added place holder for actual documentation.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="combo_edit"/> the latest addition.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="usecode_edit"/> link to latest patch and link to Pertex'documentation.</li>
				<li><ref1 target="what_next"/> 'scratched' the stuff I think got implemented.</li>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="07042002">
			<header>07 April 2002</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					This is the first draft of the <Studio/> documentation. So please bear with me. It
					is by no means perfect and I ask you to send me all your comments on how to better
					express some stuff or to point out what I just plain forgot. 
					<extref target="mailto:gigdr@tesionmail.de">Dominus</extref>
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>			
	<section title="Introduction">
		<sub name="whatis_studio">
			<header>What is <Studio/>?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<Exult/> is not only capable of playing Ultima 7 but it is also intended as
					an engine in the style of the one used by Ultima 7. <Studio/> started it's life
					as a simple map editor but it is slowly developing into a full fledged editor
					enabling users to create a new game. Tristan came up with the cool name!
				</para>
				<para>
					Currently there are many steps required to create a new game but at the moment 
					the main goal of Jeff is to make it as user-friendly as possible.
				</para>
				<para>
					Editing a copyrighted game may or may not be allowed. Please exercise caution especially
					if you want to distribute your changes.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="studio_terms">
			<header>Terms we use in regard to Exult and Ultima 7</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Along with the terms explained in <extref doc="docs" target="terms"/> there are
					some more terms that need to be explained for the usage of <Studio/>
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>tile</strong>:<br/>
						8x8 pixels</li>
					<li><strong>chunk</strong>:<br/>
						16x16 tiles</li>
					<li><strong>superchunk</strong>:<br/>
						16x16 chunks</li>
					<li><strong>world</strong>:<br/>
						12x12 superchunks</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>	
	<section title="Configurations">
		<sub name="installation">
			<header>Installation</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li>You need <Exult/> and you need to install it properly 
						(see <extref doc="docs" target="installation"/>)</li>
					<li>For U*ix platforms you need to build <Studio/> from the source avillable from our 
						source snapshot at <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/download.php"/>.<br/>
						You will also need the GTK+ library installed as well as
				<extref target="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/libglade/libglade.html">libglade</extref>.<br/></li>
					<li>For Win32 platforms (Win9x,ME,2k,XP) you need to download 
						<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/snapshots/ExultStudio.exe"/>
						and install it in the same directory where you installed <Exult/>.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="studio_run">
			<header>Running <Studio/></header>
			<body>
				<para>
					You can run <Studio/> all by itself, but it isn't useful that way,
					as it uses <Exult/> as a server.  What you really want to do is:
				</para>
				<ul>
   				<li>Put 'exult_studio.glade' in the <Exult/> 'data' directory.</li>
   				<li>Be sure 'exult_studio' is in your path. (on Win32
   					'exult_studio.exe' needs to be in the same directory as exult.exe)</li>
				<li>On U*ix platforms you need to be running <Exult/> on X.</li>
   				<li>Run <Exult/> in windowed mode (not fullscreen).</li>
   				<li>Press 'alt-ctrl-m' to go into 'map-editor' mode.  If all is set
					up correctly, exult_studio will start up, and will have a list of files
					on the left side of its window (you need to have cheats enabled in <Exult/>,
					see the <extref doc="docs" target="gameplay_gump"/>).</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					Starting up one or the other separately will reconnect them:
				</para>
				<ul>
    			<li>If <Exult/> isn't running, start it up.  Then, in <Studio/>,
					use the 'File' menu to choose the static directory (for the game you're
					playing).</li>
   				<li>If <Studio/> isn't running start it up with:
        			exult_studio -x (path to dir containing exult_studio.glade) -d
        			(path to game directory)</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					You can also reconnect by selecting File-Connect in <Studio/>'s
					menus.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="studio_cfg">
			<header>Settings in exult.cfg.</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					You can change the settings of <Studio/> either with the prefernces dialog or 
					via exult.cfg. Those settings are:
				</para>
				<configdesc>
					<line>&lt;config&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;estudio&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;main&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;width&gt;</line>
					<line>640
						<comment>** width of the program window 
						</comment></line>
					<line>&lt;/width&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;height&gt;</line>
					<line>400
						<comment>** height of the program window
						</comment></line>					
					<line>&lt;/height&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;/main&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;default_game&gt;</line>
					<line>gamename
						<comment>** default game to edit (games must be specified in 
						&lt;game&gt; part of exult.cfg)
						</comment></line>					
					<line>&lt;/default_game&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;image_editor&gt;</line>
					<line>gimp-remote -n
						<comment>** command that calls the image editor. Only useful on U*ix 
						platforms for now.
						</comment></line>
					<line>&lt;/image_editor&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;background_color&gt;</line>
					<line>0
						<comment>** background color for the shape-chooser. Use the preference 
						dialog of Exult Studio for this.
						</comment></line>
					<line>&lt;/background_color&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;/estudio&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;/config&gt;</line>
				</configdesc>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="command_line">
			<header>Command line options</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<Studio/> offers some "hidden" command line options:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li>-gGAMENAME<br/>
						specifies GAMENAME and <Studio/> will read the game base directory from exult.cfg.
						GAMENAME can be choosen from the games specified in &lt;game&gt; part of exult.cfg.</li>
					<li>-dDIRECTORY<br/>
						specifies DIRECTORY as the game base directory.</li>
					<li>-xDIRECTORY<br/>
						tells exult_studio to look in DIRECTORY for its user-interface specification 
						(exult_studio.glade).<br/>
  						This option is only useful to developers who want to edit exult_studio.glade 
  						themselves.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Menu Options">
		<sub name="file_menu">
			<header>File</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>New Game...</strong><br/>
						This lets you begin the work on a new game. Jeff wrote an extensive description of
						how to use this and how it works.<br/>
						See 
						<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/newgame.txt">New Game manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>Open Game...</strong><br/>
						Choose the Game directory of the game you want to edit.</li>
					<li><strong>Save all</strong><key>Ctrl+S</key><br/>
						Saves map, shape infos and groups you edited (see below).</li>
					<li><strong>New...</strong><br/>
						<strong>Shapes file...</strong><br/>
						Lets you choose the directory where you want to create a new vga file and requires 
						you to enter a name for it (e.g. mygame.vga).<br/>
						<strong>Single shape file...</strong><br/>
						Lets you choose the directory where you want to create a new shape file and requires 
						you to enter a name for it (e.g. mygame.shp).</li>
					<li><strong>Save...</strong><br/>
						<strong>Map</strong><br/>
						Saves the map of the edited game.<br/>
						<strong>Shape info</strong><br/>
						When you right click a shape in a vga file you can change the info of the shape.
						This saves this changed info.<br/>
						<strong>Groups</strong><br/>
						You can "bundle" shapes of vga files into groups to make world building easier. 
						These groups get saved with this option.</li>
					<li><strong>Reload...</strong><br/>
						<strong>Map</strong><key>Ctrl+R</key><br/>
						Reloads the map. All changes made since the last save get discarded.<br/>
						<strong>Usecode</strong><br/>
						Very useful when you edit the usecode of a game or add new usecode to an 
						existing game. Normally this would require a restart of Exult.</li>
					<li><strong>Connect</strong><br/>
						Connects <Exult/> and <Studio/> if one of them had to be restarted.</li>
					<li><strong>Preferences</strong><br/>
						<strong>Image Editor Command:</strong><br/>
						This executes the chosen image editor when you want to edit a shape when you
						right click it.<br/>
						<strong>Image-Edit Filetype:</strong><br/>
						Choose which filetype gets executed with the above cosen image editor.<br/>
						<strong>Default Game Name:</strong><br/>
						Choose the game <Studio/> opens by default. Use the name specified in exult.cfg.<br/>
						<strong>Shape List Background:</strong><br/>
						Sometimes the default black background may make certain shapes hard to see. Choose 
						a different background colour here.</li>
					<li><strong>Exit</strong><key>Ctrl+Q</key><br/>
						Exits <Studio/>.</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					Note that the default location for saving and creation of new files is the STATIC directory
					of a game if there is no PATCH directory specified. See <ref1 target="can_do_atm"/>.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="objects_menu">
			<header>Objects</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Egg...</strong><br/>
					Create or edit eggs with this.
					See <ref1 target="egg_edit"/> for more information (not yet there).</li>
					<li><strong>NPC...</strong><br/>
					Create or edit NPCs with this.
					See <ref1 target="npc_edit"/> for more information (not yet there).</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="mode_menu">
			<header>Mode</header>
			<body>
				<para>
				It describes how the mouse behaves inside Exult when map-editing.
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Move</strong><br/>
					This is the normal mode where you can drag things with the mouse, or single-click to 
					identify objects.</li>
					<li><strong>Paint</strong><br/>
					a single-left-click inserts the last-selected shape from 'shapes.vga', and dragging 
					with the left-button inserts that shape in every tile (so you'd probably only want 
					to do this with 8x8 flat shapes).  Also, in 'Paint' mode, the footprint at ground 
					level is shown (though this may be changed in the future).</li>
					<li><strong>Pick for Combo</strong><br/>
					Picks objects for a new combo file. See <ref1 target="combo_edit"/></li>
					<li><strong>Select</strong><br/>
					not yet implemented (?)</li>
					<li><strong>Hide</strong><br/>
					not yet implemented (?)</li>
					<li><strong>Unhide</strong><br/>
					not yet implemented (?)</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="tools_menu">
			<header>Tools</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Locator...</strong><key>Ctrl+L</key><br/>
					shows where the current game window is within the entire map, and lets you move 
					the view by double-clicking a location or by dragging the little box</li>
					<li><strong>New Combo</strong><br/>
					Creates a new Combo file. See <ref1 target="combo_edit"/>.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="tool_bar">
			<header>Tool bar</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Play Game</strong><br/>
					This is the same as pressing <key>Alt+Ctrl+M</key> in Exult. It exits the Map Edit Mode
					and lets you play the game. By pressing it again you enter Map Edit Mode again.</li>
					<li><strong>Tile Grid</strong><br/>
					Shows a grid in the game window for better control on placing objects.</li>
					<li><strong>Edit lift:</strong><br/>
					Changes the lift of a selected object in the game window. Lift means the distance of
					an object from the ground.</li>
					<li><strong>Edit terrain</strong><br/>
					See <ref1 target="can_do_atm"/>. Note that a terrain is used in multiple instances of the 
					map and changing it in one place changes it in all the others as well.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Editing a Game">
		<sub name="description">
			<header>Description</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Once <Studio/> runs correctly , a tree of game files is displayed to the left of 
					the main window, while the currently selected file is viewed in detail to the right. 
					At the moment, the following types of files are supported:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Shape files</strong><br/>
						Shapes are the basic graphical elements of the game. Each shape has one or more 
						frames that typically represent different states or angles of the same thing. 
						E.g. a button shape could have frames for pressed, and released; a character 
						could have frames depicting her sitting, standing up facing one way, or another, 
						swinging a punch, etc.<br/> 
						When a shape file is selected, the right part of the main window will show frame 
						zero of the shapes contained therein. Shapes can be selected by clicking, which 
						will show there number, number of frames, and name if known. Other frames can be 
						viewed by changing the frame number.</li>
					<li><strong>Map files</strong><br/>
						These files contain so called chunks that serve as templates in the final map. 
						The chunks of the selected map file are shown to the right of the main window.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="can_do_atm">
			<header>What you can do at the moment</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					With the latest source you can
				</para>
					<ul>
						<li>browse shapes in the main window.</li>
   						<li>drag a shape from the shape browser to <Exult/>, and that
							object will be placed in the game.</li>
   						<li>edit an 'egg' by double-clicking on it.  An edit box
							should appear.</li>
   						<li>create a new 'egg' using the pull-down menu in <Studio/>.
							In the Egg edit box, after you hit 'Apply', you'll be prompted to
							click in <Exult/> where you want the egg to appear.</li>
   						<li>If editing a 'monster' egg, you can set the monster by dragging
							the shape from the browser to the area that displays the monster.</li>
						<li>edit an NPC by double-clicking on it, and also create a new
							NPC using the pull-down menu.  Attributes, flags, and schedules can
							all be viewed and modified.</li>
						<li>can edit other objects' position and quality by double-clicking on them.</li>
						<li>browse the 'u7chunks' file, and drag them into <Exult/> to change
							the terrain.  In this browser, you can also create new terrains and
							modify their order.</li>
						<li>edit a 'terrain' (stored in 'u7chunks') by clicking the "Edit
							terrain" checkbox in <Studio/>.  This is a special mode where
							dragging with the left mouse button 'paints' the currently-selected
							shape (generally one of the flat tiles near the top of the shapes
							browser).  Note that a 'terrain' is generally used in multiple places
							in the mapand changing it in one place changes it in all the others as well.</li>
						<li>save the map using ExultStudio's "File-Save map" pulldown.
							In order to avoid writing over files inadvertantly, the files that
							would normally go into the 'static' directory, will, instead, go into
							a 'patch' directory that you specify in your 'exult.cfg' file.  Here's
							an example for editing BG:</li>
					</ul>
				<configdesc>
					<line>&lt;game&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;blackgate&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;path&gt;</line>
					<line>blackgate</line>
					<line>&lt;/path&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;patch&gt;</line>
					<line>blackgate/patch</line>
					<line>&lt;/patch&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;title&gt;</line>
					<line>blackgate</line>
					<line>&lt;/title&gt;</line>
					<line>.</line>
					<line>&lt;/blackgate&gt;</line>
				</configdesc>
				<para>
					<Exult/> will also read files from 'patch' if it exists on starting a new game.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="shape_edit">
			<header>The shape editor</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					When you right click on a shape in the Shape browser (e.g. Files-Shapes.vga) you 
					get some options of how to edit the shapes.
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Edit...</strong>:<br/>
						Brings up your image-editor on the chosen frame.  When you save 
						in the image-editor, ES will read the changes back within 5 seconds.  This is 
						especially convenient if you have 'gimp-remote', as it will open a window for 
						the frame in an already-running gimp.</li>
					<li><strong>Edit tiled</strong>:<br/>
						This is only for 'flat' (8x8) shapes.  It forms an image 
						from all the frames and brings it up in the image-editor.  This is really 
						handy for making lots of terrain frames like grass.  A dialog lets you choose 
						the dimensions.</li>
					<li><strong>New frame</strong>:<br/>
						Creates a new frame after the currently-selected one.  The 'insert' key 
						also does this (and the 'del' key deletes a frame, though it's 
						buggy if there's just one frame left).</li>
					<li><strong>New shape</strong>:<br/>
						Gives you a dialog for choosing the shape #, as well as the 
						initial # of frames.</li>
					<li><strong>Import/Export frame</strong>:<br/>
						Let's you import a single frame from a .png file or 
						export to a .png.</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					<em>Note:</em><strong>Edit...</strong> doesn't work on Windows system. It stores 
					the sahpe as PNG file in GAMEDIR/itmp/ (e.g. blackgate/itmp). If you manually
					open the file with an image editor of your liking and then save it, ES doesn't 
					read the changes back.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="egg_edit">
			<header>Creating/editing Eggs</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					sorry, not documented yet (very extensive work). But make sure you resize the egg-window 
					to show all the possible eggs. To know what 'egg' means, see 
					<extref doc="docs" target="terms"/>.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="npc_edit">
			<header>Creating/editing NPCs</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					sorry, not documented yet (very extensive work).
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="combo_edit">
			<header>Creating Combination files</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Create 'combination shapes', like a fence or an entire roof by selecting 
					"Tools-New Combo" (see <ref target="tools_menu"/>).  It's about half-done.
					To see what's there, choose the 'Combo pick' choice in the 'Modes' menu, and 
					an empty window should pop up. In the game window, double-click a group of objects,
					and they should appear in the window.  You can then select an object there and tweak 
					its position.  Nothing gets saved yet.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="usecode_edit">
			<header>Custom Usecode</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					As hinted at (see <extref doc="docs" target="terms"/>) Usecode is actually what runs Ultima 7
					and therefore any game created with <Studio/>.<br/>
					As of yet we do not have a Usecode editor/debugger. So writing your own Usecode is not 
					that easy.
				</para>
				<para>
					For an example of how Usecode may look like download our experimental patch for BG at
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/snapshots/patch.zip"/>.<br/>
					In that zip you'll find a readme.txt which tells you how to run it.<br/>
					You will also see two files called usecode.uc and usecode.
				</para>
				<para>
					Usecode.uc is the usecode script that will help you understand our usecode language.<br/>
					When you run ucc (see <ref target="tools"/>) with that file 
					(e.g. "ucc -o usecode usecode.uc") you will get the file called usecode. This file 
					'usecode' should be the same as the one in the zip file.
				</para>
				<para>
					Someone does have to write extensive documentation for this but I (Dominus) am not
					really up for that task.<br/>
					Pertex has written some documentation at <extref target="http://www.sophen.de/exult/"/>
					that might be able help you.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Miscellaneous">
		<sub name="tools">
			<header>Other tools that might be useful</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					In the process of creating <Exult/> the team came up with some useful 
					tools that might help in editing/making a game.<br/>
					These can be built from the <Exult/> source or you can download
					the Windows binary snapshot. The source and binary snapshot can be found at
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/download.php"/>.<br/>
					The tools are:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>expack</strong>:<br/>
						lets you extract and create Flex files. 
						See <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/expack.txt">manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>ipack</strong>:<br/>
						a tool for creating and updating Exult and U7 image archives,  such as 'shapes.vga'. 
						See <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/ipack.txt">manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>shp2pcx</strong>:<br/>
						converts all frames contained in a Shape file into PCX-format image files. 
						See <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/shp2pcx.txt">manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>splitshp</strong>:<br/>
						can be used to combine frames of a Shape file into one file, or split a Shape 
						file into its component frames. 
						See <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/splitshp.txt">manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>textpack</strong>:<br/>
						can be used edit text flex files. 
						See <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/textpack.txt">manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>ucc</strong>:<br/>
						can be used to create custom usecode (see <ref target="usecode_edit"/>).</li>
					<li><strong>The GIMP Plug-in</strong>:<br/>
						can be used for editing shapes in the GIMP. Handles multiframe Shape files. 
						See <extref target="http://www.gimp.org"/> for inormation on the GIMP.</li>
					<li><strong>Photoshop Plug-in</strong>:<br/>
						can be used for editing shapes in Photoshop. Can't handle multiframe Shape files. And 
						also can't handle indexed images with Alpha correctly.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="port_platforms">
			<header>Porting <Studio/> to other platforms</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Currently <Studio/> runs on U*ix and Windows platforms. First it only
					ran on U*ix but with some effort by Colourless, Kirben and Mark Siewert
					it was succesfully ported to Win32.
				</para>
				<para>
					A port to other platforms depends on when someone volunteers to do the work :-)
					There are three issues:
				</para>
				<ul>
   				<li>GTK has to be ported to the platform.</li>
   				<li><Studio/> uses sockets to communicate with <Exult/>.</li>
   				<li>X drag-n-drop is used to put new objects on the landscape.  The
					'drop' part of this had to be rewritten for Win32 <Exult/>, OR,
					drag-n-drop could be an enhancement to SDL someday.<br/>
					As an alternative to dragging objects, you can now select a shape,
					then insert it into the game window by left-clicking while holding the
					Shift key down.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>	
		<sub name="client_server_stuff">
			<header>About this client/server stuff?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					A map-editor needs to provide the ability to display the game, place
					objects on the map, and move objects around.  That functionality is already in
					<Exult/>, and it makes sense to reuse it.  So we could have made <Exult/> a part of
					<Studio/>.  However, <Exult/> is already a huge program, and is getting
					unwieldy to work on.
				</para>
				<para>
					With this architecture, <Studio/> can have all the messy code for
					displaying/editing dialog boxes, while <Exult/> only needs a little bit
					of work to handle requests.
				</para>
				<para>
					Also, I (Jeff) wanted to get a little experience programming with
					sockets:-)
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="terrain_stuff">
			<header>About this 'terrain-editing' stuff and why you can't just
  					drag objects to where you want.</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					This confused me too, and I originally planned on doing away with it.
					But do a little arithmetic:  U7's world has 3072x3072 tiles; that's
					over 9 million that need to be set.  My guess is that they came up
					with the idea behind 'u7chunks' to save artists time and to give the
					map a consistent look.
				</para>
				<para>
					The basic idea is that each 'chunk' of flat terrain, 16x16 tiles, is
					stored in 'u7chunks', and is indexed by its position in this file (0,
					1, 2, ...). The 'u7map' file specifies, for each 'chunk' in the U7
					map, which of the terrains is to be used.  Since the entire map has
					192x192 chunks, or a total of 36,864, and since 'u7chunks' has 3072
					entries, each terrain is shared an average of over 10 times.  When you
					go into map-editing mode in Exult, the numbers displayed are the
					indices from 'u7chunks'.
				</para>
				<para>
					So here are the three sorts of scenery that you can see and edit:
				</para>
				<ol>
					<li>The 'terrain' (flat landscape, rocks, shrubs, and first-story
    					buildings) specified in 'u7chunks' and 'u7map'.</li>
    				<li>Other non-moveable objects (second-floor structures, trees) specified in
    					the 'ifixnn' files.</li>
    				<li>Moveable and changeable objects specified in the 'iregnn' files.</li>
				</ol>
				<para>
					The challenge of writing a map-editor is keeping the above straight,
					and reading/storing from/to the correct files.  It's sorta-kinda
					working now :-)
				</para>
				<para>
					For a more detailed explanation, see Gary Thompson's paper,
					'u7edit.txt' in our 'docs' directory.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="what_next">
			<header>What's next?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The next things to be implemented are:
				</para>
				<ul>
				<li><Studio/>needs to be able to automatically create palettes 1-n from palette 0 
					using the code from ipack. </li>
				<li>It will also be very nice to have a Usecode debugger someday as well 
					(Willem is actually working on it).</li>
   				<li>A 'flags' editor for viewing and editing the global Usecode flags by name.</li>
				<li>A 'barge' editor for creating things like ships and carts.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
  	<section title="Credits">
		<sub name="thanks">
			<header>Thanks</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li>Colourless, Kirben and Mark Siewart invested a lot of effort to port
					<Studio/> to Win32.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
</studiodoc>