<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE studiodoc SYSTEM "docs.dtd">
<studiodoc title="Exult" changed="28 October 2002(GMT)">
	<section title="Changes to the Documentation">
		<sub name="28102002">
			<header>28 October 2002</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li><ref1 target="studio_terms"/> added NPC schedules.</li>
					<li><ref1 target="studio_run"/> the -d command line arg is now -gGAME.</li>
					<li><ref1 target="can_do_atm"/> 'Paint with chunk' added.</li>
					<li><ref1 target="shape_files"/> 'Frames' mode mentioned and explained.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="23102002">
			<header>23 October 2002</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li>Currently I'm trying to merge my docs with the great work by Jeffrey Hoeksma. So many
						things changed that it's no use listing all the changes. And please take our many
						spelling and grammar mistakes with humor!</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>			
	<section title="Introduction">
		<sub name="whatis_studio">
			<header>What is <Studio/>?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<Exult/> is not only capable of playing Ultima 7 but it is also intended as
					an engine in the style of the one used by Ultima 7. <Studio/> started it's life
					as a simple map editor but it is slowly developing into a full fledged editor
					enabling users to create a new game. Tristan came up with the cool name!
				</para>
				<para>
					The main purpose of <Studio/> is the ability to create an entirely original 
					game world without using the original Ultima 7 data files. Its semi-possible 
					already but still requires a lot of work. Not the least of which is that an entire 
					games worth of art needs to be created.
				</para>
				<para>
					Editing a copyrighted game may or may not be allowed. Please exercise caution especially
					if you want to distribute your changes.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="about_doc">
			<header>About this Documentation.</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<Studio/> is work in progress. How things work may change and new features are
					added very frequently. Due to that the maintainers (Jeffrey, Dominus) of this 
					documentation may not have been able to update it. As we do not have an official
					release yet this documentation refers to recent snapshots.
				</para>
				<para>
					This guide is what we hope will be an ongoing effort to provide up to date and 
					in-depth information on how to get the most out of <Studio/>. Accuracy is an 
					essential part of this guide. If you find something that could be clearer or doesn't
					seem worded properly please tell us, we will be happy to change this guide. Tips and 
					tricks by other users will be appreciated as well and will of course be credited.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="studio_terms">
			<header>Terms we use in regard to Exult and Ultima 7</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Of course the terms explained in <extref doc="docs" target="terms"/> are
					also used in this Documentation but we will list them along with the terms 
					that additionally need to be explained for the usage of <Studio/>
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>tile</strong>:<br/>
						8x8 pixels</li>
					<li><strong>chunk</strong>:<br/>
						16x16 tiles</li>
					<li><strong>superchunk</strong>:<br/>
						16x16 chunks</li>
					<li><strong>world</strong>:<br/>
						12x12 superchunks</li>
					<li><strong>NPC schedules</strong>:<br/>
						NPCs can have schedules which make them do certain things at certain times.</li>
					<li><strong>BG</strong>, <strong>SI</strong>, <strong>FoV</strong> 
					or <strong>SS</strong>:<br/>
						we refer to "Ultima 7: The Black Gate" as BG and to "Ultima 7: Serpent Isle"
						as SI. The add-ons "Forge of Virtue" and "Silver Seed" are called FoV and SS.</li>
					<li><strong>eggs</strong>:<br/>
						these are trip-wires that cause monsters to spawn, execute scripts, play music, 
						change weather, trigger traps, teleport when you get near them.</li>
					<li><strong>flex files</strong>:<br/>
						or flexes are used by the original to store the data files.
						Also when you choose not use compressed save games (see save_compression_level in
						<extref doc="docs" target="exult_config"/>) our save games are also "flexed".</li>
					<li><strong>gumps</strong>:<br/>
						the windows used in the game interface for containers, characters, menus, etc..</li>
					<li><strong>paperdoll</strong>:<br/>
						when pressing <key>i</key> you get the inventory display. It's the picture of your 
						characters body (or the bodies of your party members) onto which you can drag all 
						kinds of equipment. The way this is displayed in SI is what we call 
						<strong>paperdoll</strong>. We integrated this for BG as well. 
						(see <extref doc="faq" target="improvements"/>).</li>
					<li><strong>shapes</strong>:<br/>
						shape files are the format used for storage of all graphics elements (from UI buttons 
						to terrain features) of the games Exult supports. Shapes may contain one or more 
						frames (a frame is a single image).</li>
					<li><strong>snapshot</strong>:<br/>
						see <extref doc="faq" target="whatis_snapshot"/>.<br/>
						Please note that our documentation usually refers to the latest snapshot.</li>
					<li><strong>usecode</strong>:<br/>
						that's the scripting language that drives all of U7 (conversations, objects...).</li>
					<li><strong>Exult data directory</strong>:<br/>
						that's the directory where Exult stores its data files (exult.flx, exult_bg.flx and 
						exult_si.flx).</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>	
	<section title="Configurations">
		<sub name="installation">
			<header>Installation</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li>You need <Exult/> and you need to install it properly 
						(see <extref doc="docs" target="installation"/>). Also make sure that
						you are using the <strong>latest snapshot of the 1.1.x branch</strong> of <Exult/>.</li>
					<li>For U*ix platforms you need to build <Studio/> from the source avilable from our 
						source snapshot at <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/download.php"/>.<br/>
						You will also need the GTK+ library installed as well as
				<extref target="http://developer.gnome.org/doc/API/libglade/libglade.html">libglade</extref>.<br/></li>
					<li>For Win32 platforms (Win9x,ME,2k,XP) you need to download 
						<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/snapshots/2.0/ExultStudio.exe"/>
						and install it in the same directory where you installed <Exult/>.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="studio_run">
			<header>Running <Studio/></header>
			<body>
				<para>
					You can run <Studio/> all by itself, but it isn't useful that way,
					as it uses <Exult/> as a server. What you really want to do is:
				</para>
				<ul>
   				<li>Put 'exult_studio.glade' in the <Exult/> 'data' directory.</li>
   				<li>Be sure 'exult_studio' is in your path. (on Win32
   					'exult_studio.exe' needs to be in the same directory as exult.exe)</li>
				<li>On U*ix platforms you need to be running <Exult/> on X.</li>
   				<li>Run <Exult/> in <strong>windowed mode</strong> (not fullscreen).</li>
   				<li>Press 'alt+ctrl+m' to go into 'map-editor' mode. If all is set
					up correctly, exult_studio will start up, and will have a list of files
					on the left side of its window (you need to have cheats enabled in <Exult/>,
					see the <extref doc="docs" target="gameplay_gump"/>).</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					Starting up one or the other separately will reconnect them:
				</para>
				<ul>
    			<li>If <Exult/> isn't running, start it up. Then, in <Studio/>,
					use the 'File' menu to choose the static directory (for the game you're
					playing).</li>
   				<li>If <Studio/> isn't running start it up with:
        			exult_studio -x (path to dir containing exult_studio.glade) -gGAME
        			(GAME is the same string (ie, 'blackgate') that we use in .exult.cfg or that 
        			you've given to your own game).</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					You can also reconnect by selecting File-Connect in <Studio/>'s
					menus.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="run_steps">
			<header>Step-by-step instructions to run <Studio/></header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The above instructions may still be too technical for everybody.					  
					You have to make sure all these steps are taken care of before you're going to get 
					very far with your world building.
				</para>
				<ol>
				<li>While it is not explicitly needed it is usefull to have a working copy of either 
					BG or SI properly installed onto your computer.</li>
				<li>Next, you need to have the Exult 1.1x snapshot and the SDL mixer installed properly 
					onto your computer and working correctly. If you are currently playing either BG or SI 
					on your machine this is probably done right. To make sure you have the correct version,
					ensure that it says 1.10 CVS during Exult's start-up screen.</li>
				<li>You need to make sure the newest version of <Studio/> is installed properly onto your 
					computer as well. <Studio/> should be installed in the same directory as the Exult 1.10x 
					snapshot.</li>
				<li>In order for <Studio/> to work properly, you need to have <Exult/> running in windowed mode. 
					If you can see your desktop while playing, then you're doing it right.</li>
				<li>Make sure you have Cheats enabled. This can be enabled int eh Gameplay options of the Game 
					menu.</li>
				<li>While running <Exult/> in windowed mode, hit <key>ctrl+alt+m</key> to enter map-editing mode. 
					<Studio/> should open up if you did everything correctly. In map-editing mode the world is 
					frozen, but you are still able to move your characters around in order to place objects.
					You're now ready to start your world editing. You should be seeing something like this:<br/>
					<img alt="game window with red grid" src="images/studio1.jpg"/></li>
				</ol>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="can_do_atm">
			<header>What you can do at the moment</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					With the latest source you can
				</para>
					<ul>
						<li>browse shapes in the main window.</li>
   						<li>drag a shape from the shape browser to <Exult/>, and that
							object will be placed in the game.</li>
   						<li>edit an 'egg' by double-clicking on it. An edit box
							should appear.</li>
   						<li>create a new 'egg' using the pull-down menu in <Studio/>.
							In the Egg edit box, after you hit 'Apply', you'll be prompted to
							click in <Exult/> where you want the egg to appear.</li>
   						<li>if editing a 'monster' egg, you can set the monster by dragging
							the shape from the browser to the area that displays the monster.</li>
						<li>edit an NPC by double-clicking on it, and also create a new
							NPC using the pull-down menu. Attributes, flags, and schedules can
							all be viewed and modified.</li>
						<li>edit other objects' position and quality by double-clicking on them.</li>
						<li>browse the 'u7chunks' file, and drag them into <Exult/> to change
							the terrain. In this browser, you can also create new terrains and
							modify their order.</li>
						<li>select a chunk, choose 'Paint with chunks' from the 'Mode' menu, and then 
							paint terrain with that whole chunk.</li>	
						<li>edit a 'terrain' (stored in 'u7chunks') by clicking the "Edit
							terrain" checkbox in <Studio/>. This is a special mode where
							dragging with the left mouse button 'paints' the currently-selected
							shape (generally one of the flat tiles near the top of the shapes
							browser). Note that a 'terrain' is generally used in multiple places
							in the map and changing it in one place changes it in all the others as well.</li>
						<li>save the map using <Studio/>'s "File-Save map" pulldown menu.
							In order to avoid writing over files inadvertently, the files that
							would normally go into the 'static' directory, will, instead, go into
							a 'patch' directory that you specify in your 'exult.cfg' file. Here's
							an example for editing BG:</li>
					</ul>
				<configdesc>
					<line>&lt;game&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;blackgate&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;path&gt;</line>
					<line>blackgate</line>
					<line>&lt;/path&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;patch&gt;</line>
					<line>blackgate/patch</line>
					<line>&lt;/patch&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;title&gt;</line>
					<line>blackgate</line>
					<line>&lt;/title&gt;</line>
					<line>.</line>
					<line>&lt;/blackgate&gt;</line>
				</configdesc>
				<para>
					<Exult/> will also read files from 'patch' if it exists on starting a new game.
				</para>
				<para>
					In any mode, you can add the currently selected shape by shift-clicking..
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="studio_cfg">
			<header>Settings in exult.cfg.</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					You can change the settings of <Studio/> either with the preferences dialog or 
					via exult.cfg. Those settings are:
				</para>
				<configdesc>
					<line>&lt;config&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;estudio&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;main&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;width&gt;</line>
					<line>640
						<comment>** width of the program window 
						</comment></line>
					<line>&lt;/width&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;height&gt;</line>
					<line>400
						<comment>** height of the program window
						</comment></line>					
					<line>&lt;/height&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;/main&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;default_game&gt;</line>
					<line>gamename
						<comment>** default game to edit (games must be specified in 
						&lt;game&gt; part of exult.cfg)
						</comment></line>					
					<line>&lt;/default_game&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;image_editor&gt;</line>
					<line>gimp-remote -n
						<comment>** command that calls the image editor. Only useful on U*ix 
						platforms for now.
						</comment></line>
					<line>&lt;/image_editor&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;background_color&gt;</line>
					<line>0
						<comment>** background color for the shape-chooser. Use the preference 
						dialog of Exult Studio for this.
						</comment></line>
					<line>&lt;/background_color&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;/estudio&gt;</line>
					<line>&lt;/config&gt;</line>
				</configdesc>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="command_line">
			<header>Command line options</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<Studio/> offers some "hidden" command line options:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li>-gGAMENAME<br/>
						specifies GAMENAME and <Studio/> will read the game base directory from exult.cfg.
						GAMENAME can be chosen from the games specified in &lt;game&gt; part of exult.cfg.</li>
					<li>-xDIRECTORY<br/>
						tells exult_studio to look in DIRECTORY for its user-interface specification 
						(exult_studio.glade).<br/>
						You can enter the full path (e.g. "exult_studio -xc:\exult\data") to the glade file 
						or you can use the relative path (e.g. exult_studio -x./data).<br/>
  						This option is only useful to developers who want to edit exult_studio.glade 
  						themselves.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
		<section title="Exult Studio basics">
		<sub name="overview">
			<header>Description</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Once <Studio/> runs correctly , a tree of game files is displayed to the left of 
					the main window, while the currently selected file is viewed in detail to the right.<br/>
					<img alt="Exult Studio default view" src="images/studio2.jpg"/><br/>
					The types of files <Studio/> supports are described next.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="shape_files">
			<header>Shape files</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Shapes are the basic graphical elements of the game. Each shape has one or more 
					frames that typically represent different states or angles of the same thing. 
					E.g. a button shape could have frames for pressed, and released; a character 
					could have frames depicting her sitting, standing up facing one way, or another, 
					swinging a punch, etc.<br/> 
					When a shape file is selected, the right part of the main window will show frame 
					zero of the shapes contained therein. Shapes can be selected by clicking, which 
					will show there number, number of frames, and name if known. Other frames can be 
					viewed by changing the frame number.
				</para>
				<para>
					When the selected file contains shapes that have names in their info you can also use
					the find option to find shapes that have that name (e.g. in shapes.vga you can search 
					for 'door' to find all shapes that have door frames). You can search down or up in the
					selected file.
				</para>
				<para>
					When viewing shapes you can press the button 'Frames' in the lower right corner of 
					<Studio/> to show all the frames of a shape next to each others.
				</para>				
				<para>
					Shape files also have a special right-click-menu. See <ref1 target="shape_edit"/>.
				</para>
				<para>
					Typicall shape files are:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Sprites.vga</strong><br/>
						displays all the animations that can be used to overlay the screen.</li>
					<li><strong>Shapes.vga</strong><br/>
						displays the objects that can be placed onto the world.</li>
					<li><strong>Fonts.vga</strong><br/>
						displays all text graphics used throughout the game.</li>
					<li><strong>Faces.vga</strong><br/>
						contains all of the graphics for conversation pictures..</li>
					<li><strong>Pointers.shp</strong><br/>
						contains the graphics for the mouse cursor.</li>
					<li><strong>Combos.flx</strong><br/>
						where custom made combos will be stored.</li>
				</ul>
				
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="map_files">
			<header>Map files</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					These files contain so called chunks that serve as templates in the final map. 
					The chunks of the selected map file are shown in the right part of the main window.<br/>
					When a chunk is selected you have two options below:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Locate</strong><br/>
						shows places in the <Exult/> game where that chunk is used.</li>
					<li><strong>Move</strong><br/>
						Moves a chunk in the chunk file. This does not effect the display on the map.</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					Right clicking on a chunk gives you another two options 
					(also the File-save/revert option):
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>New...</strong><br/>
						<strong>Empty</strong><br/>
						Creates a new chunk. Drag the new chunk onto the game and edit it by dragging 
						shapes on it.<br/>
						<strong>Duplicate</strong><br/>
						Duplicates a chunk. Drag the duplicate chunk onto the map to edit it.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="palettes_files">
			<header>Palettes files</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The palettes used by a game are stored in the files listed there.<br/>
					When you select a palette with number zero is shown in the right part of the main 
					window. Other palettes are shown by selecting another palettes number  
					When a palettes file is selected you have some options:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Edit</strong><br/>
						New/Remove adds or deletes a palettes.</li>
					<li><strong>Move</strong><br/>
						Moves palettes in the file.</li>
					<li><strong>File</strong><br/>
						<strong>Import</strong><br/>
						Overwrites the current palettes with palette text file.<br/>
						<strong>Export</strong><br/>
						Exports the current palette to a text file.</li>						
				</ul>
				<para>
					Right clicking on a chunk only gives you the default File-save/revert option.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="groups_files">
			<header>Groups files</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Editing a game can become quite cumbersome when you have to choose between a lot
					of shape files containing several frames. To make this task easier we have 
					implemented so called groups to groups several shapes together. For example you can 
					group all shapes containing door frames together in a group called 'doors'.<br/>
					For this you have to select Groups and create a new group by writing the name in the 
					lower part of the window and then click 'add'. You now have the option in the Shape 
					Menu to add a shape to this group.<br/>
					When you double-click a group the group window opens that shows the shapes in the group 
					and by selecting a shape you see the shape info.
					You also have some options to edit the group:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Move</strong><br/>
						Moves the shapes within the group.</li>
					<li><strong>Remove</strong><br/>
						Removes the shape from the group.</li>
					<li><strong>Name</strong><br/>						
						Changes the name of the group.</li>
					<li><strong>Frame:</strong><br/>						
						select the frame displayed.</li>
					<li><strong>Frames</strong><br/>						
						shows all the frames of a shape next to each others.</li>
					<li><strong>Find</strong><br/>						
						Lets you search for a specified shape in the group.</li>
					<li><strong>Locate</strong><br/>						
						Locates the selected shape inside the game. It locates only the shape not a 
						specific frame.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="detail_window">
			<header>The detail window</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Below the detail windows you have the following options:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Frame:</strong><br/>						
						select the frame displayed.</li>
					<li><strong>Frames</strong><br/>						
						shows all the frames of a shape next to each others.</li>
					<li><strong>Find</strong><br/>						
						Lets you search for a specified shape in the group.</li>
					<li><strong>Locate</strong><br/>						
						Locates the selected shape inside the game. It locates only the shape not a 
						specific frame.</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					<strong>Right-clicking on the detailed view of any file gives these options</strong> 
					(along with other options specific to the file):
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>File...</strong><br/>
						<strong>Save</strong><br/>
						Saves all the changes you made to it without saving any other file.<br/>
						<strong>Revert</strong><br/>
						Discards all changes..</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Exult Studio's menus">
		<sub name="overview">
			<header>An overview</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Before you get started with constructing your own little world its important to know 
					a little bit about the structure of <Studio/> and the arrangement of menus. An 
					overview of some of the <Studio/> menus follows.<br/>
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="file_menu">
			<header>File</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>New Game...</strong><br/>
						This lets you begin the work on a new game. Jeff wrote an extensive description of
						how to use this and how it works.<br/>
						See 
						<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/newgame.txt">New Game manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>Open Game...</strong><br/>
						Choose the Game directory of the game you that you have been working on.</li>
					<li><strong>Save all</strong><key>Ctrl+S</key><br/>
						Saves map, shape info and groups you edited. Saves all the changes you've made to 
						the world you have been working on. If you're happy with your changes do this 
						before you quit or all work will be lost.</li>
					<li><strong>New...</strong><br/>
						<strong>Shapes file...</strong><br/>
						Lets you choose the directory where you want to create a new vga file and requires 
						you to enter a name for it (e.g. mygame.vga).<br/>
						<strong>Single shape file...</strong><br/>
						Lets you choose the directory where you want to create a new shape file and requires 
						you to enter a name for it (e.g. mygame.shp).</li>
					<li><strong>Save...</strong><br/>
						<strong>Map</strong><br/>
						Saves the map of the edited game.<br/>
						<strong>Shape info</strong><br/>
						When you right click a shape in a vga file you can change the info of the shape.
						This saves this changed info.<br/>
						<strong>Groups</strong><br/>
						You can "bundle" shapes of vga files into groups to make world building easier. 
						These groups get saved with this option.<br/>
						<strong>Combos</strong><br/>
						This saves the combination files.</li>						
					<li><strong>Reload...</strong><br/>
						<strong>Map</strong><key>Ctrl+R</key><br/>
						Reloads the map. All changes made since the last save get discarded.<br/>
						<strong>Usecode</strong><br/>
						Very useful when you edit the usecode of a game or add new usecode to an 
						existing game. Normally this would require a restart of Exult.</li>
					<li><strong>Connect</strong><br/>
						Connects <Exult/> and <Studio/> if one of them had to be restarted.</li>
					<li><strong>Preferences</strong><br/>
						<strong>Image Editor Command:</strong><br/>
						This executes the chosen image editor when you want to edit a shape when you
						right click it.<br/>
						<strong>Image-Edit Filetype:</strong><br/>
						Choose which filetype gets executed with the above chosen image editor.<br/>
						<strong>Default Game Name:</strong><br/>
						Choose the game <Studio/> opens by default. Use the name specified in exult.cfg.<br/>
						<strong>Shape List Background:</strong><br/>
						Sometimes the default black background may make certain shapes hard to see. Choose 
						a different background color here.</li>
					<li><strong>Exit</strong><key>Ctrl+Q</key><br/>
						Exits <Studio/>.</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					Note that the default location for saving and creation of new files is the STATIC directory
					of a game if there is no PATCH directory specified. See <ref1 target="can_do_atm"/>.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="edit_menu">
			<header>Edit</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Cut  </strong><key>Ctrl+X</key><br/>
					Removes the selected object(s) and puts it into memory.</li>
					<li><strong>Copy  </strong><key>Ctrl+C</key><br/>
					Copies the selected object(s) into memory.</li>
					<li><strong>Paste  </strong><key>Ctrl+V</key><br/>
					Shows the crosshair cursor and copies the object(s) from the memory into the game
					where you left click the crosshair.</li>
					<li><strong>Properties...</strong><br/>
					Shows the properties of the selected object. If more than one object is selected
					it shows the properties of the last selected object.<br/>
					Only NPCs and eggs show different properties than if you select Basic properties.</li>
					<li><strong>Basic properties...</strong><br/>
					Shows the properties of the selected object. If more than one object is selected
					it shows the properties of the last selected object.</li>
					<li><strong>Create egg...</strong><br/>
					Create or edit eggs with this.
					See <section_ref target="Egg editing"/> for detailed information.</li>
					<li><strong>Create NPC...</strong><br/>
					Create or edit NPCs with this.
					See <section_ref target="NPC editing"/> for more information (not yet there).</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="mode_menu">
			<header>Mode</header>
			<body>
				<para>
				It describes how the mouse behaves inside <Exult/> when map-editing.
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Move</strong><br/>
					This is the normal mode where you can drag things with the mouse, or single-click 
					to identify objects. In this mode you also select objects. A selected object is 
					shown with a red outline. To select more than one object hold down <key>Ctrl</key> 
					while selecting. Move the selection <key>Ctrl+arrow</key> (x,y coordinates) and 
					<key>Ctrl+page</key> keys (z coordinates).</li>
					<li><strong>Paint</strong><br/>
					a single-left-click inserts the last-selected shape from 'shapes.vga', and dragging 
					with the left-button inserts that shape in every tile (so you'd probably only want 
					to do this with 8x8 flat shapes). Also, in 'Paint' mode, the footprint at ground 
					level is shown (though this may be changed in the future).<br/>
					If you hold the alt key down, random frames from the currently-selected shape will 
					be painted (handy for grassy areas).</li>
					<li><strong>Paint with chunks</strong><br/>
					works the same as the normal Paint mode only with chunks. Left-clicking the mouse
					paints the current chunk onto the map.<br/>
					Take a look at <ref1 target="change_chunks"/>.</li>
					<li><strong>Pick for Combo</strong><br/>
					Picks objects for a new combo file. Double-left-click to add objects to the combo, 
					single-left-click to identify object. See <ref1 target="combo_edit"/></li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					Note that you can only drag objects in the game window when you are in "Move" mode.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="tools_menu">
			<header>Tools</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Locator...</strong><key>Ctrl+L</key><br/>
					shows where the current game window is within the entire map, and lets you move 
					the view by double-clicking a location or by dragging the little box</li>
					<li><strong>New Combo..</strong><br/>
					Creates a new Combo file. See <ref1 target="combo_edit"/>.</li>
					<li><strong>Unused shapes...</strong><br/>
					searches the entire world being created to see if any of the shapes in shapes.vga 
					are not in use. Have patience when doing this and treat the results with caution.</li>
					<li><strong>Compile Usecode...</strong><br/>
					Compiles the usecode script usecode.uc in the patch directory 
					(see <ref target="usecode_edit"/>)</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="tool_bar">
			<header>Tool bar</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Play</strong><br/>
					This is the same as pressing <key>Alt+Ctrl+M</key> in Exult. It exits the Map Edit Mode
					and lets you play the game. By pressing it again you enter Map Edit Mode again.</li>
					<li><strong>Grid</strong><br/>
					Shows a grid of white lines in the game window for better control on placing objects.</li>
					<li><strong>Edit lift:</strong><br/>
					Changes the lift of a selected object in the game window. Lift means the distance of
					an object from the ground.</li>
					<li><strong>Hide lift:</strong><br/>
					Hides objects that are above the chosen height.</li>
					<li><strong>Edit terrain</strong><br/>
					See <ref1 target="can_do_atm"/>. Note that a terrain is used in multiple instances of the 
					map and changing it in one place changes it in all the others as well.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Basic editors">		
		<sub name="shape_edit">
			<header>The shape editor</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					When you right click on a shape in the Shape browser (e.g. Files-Shapes.vga) you 
					get some options of how to edit the shapes.
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Add to group...</strong><br/>
						If you set up groups you can add shapes to them with this.</li>
					<li><strong>Info...</strong><br/>
						Displays the information of an object. You can change a lot of stuff there and 
						caution is advised. The information is saved by 
						<ref1 target="file_menu">'Save all' or 'Save:Shape Info'</ref1>.</li>
					<li><strong>Edit...</strong>:<br/>
						Brings up your image-editor on the chosen frame. When you save 
						in the image-editor, ES will read the changes back within 5 seconds. This is 
						especially convenient if you have 'gimp-remote', as it will open a window for 
						the frame in an already-running gimp.</li>
					<li><strong>Edit tiled</strong>:<br/>
						This is only for 'flat' (8x8) shapes. It forms an image 
						from all the frames and brings it up in the image-editor. This is really 
						handy for making lots of terrain frames like grass. A dialog lets you choose 
						the dimensions.</li>
					<li><strong>New frame</strong>:<br/>
						Creates a new frame after the currently-selected one. The 'insert' key 
						also does this (and the 'del' key deletes a frame, though it's 
						buggy if there's just one frame left).</li>
					<li><strong>New shape</strong>:<br/>
						Gives you a dialog for choosing the shape #, as well as the 
						initial # of frames.<br/>
						You can also create a new font shape from TrueType or Type1 font files.
						It's mainly a convenience for someone creating a whole new game, as their
						only single-colored. Maybe in the future we'll have some functions to
						create two-colored fonts like the main one in U7, although it might take
						hand-editing to make the letters look that nice.</li>
					<li><strong>Import/Export frame</strong>:<br/>
						Let's you import a single frame from a .png file or 
						export to a .png.</li>
				</ul>
				<para>
					<em>Note:</em> <strong>Edit...</strong> doesn't work on Windows system. It stores 
					the shape as PNG file in GAMEDIR/itmp/ (e.g. blackgate/itmp). If you manually
					open the file with an image editor of your liking and then save it, ES doesn't 
					read the changes back.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="combo_edit">
			<header>Creating Combination files</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Create 'combination shapes', like a fence or an entire roof by selecting 
					"Tools-New Combo" (see <ref target="tools_menu"/>). When you run <Studio/> the first
					time a file called combos.flx gets automatically created in the "Patch" directory.
					Choose the 'Pick for Combo' choice in the 'Modes' menu, and an empty window should 
					pop up. In the game window, double-click a group of objects, and they should appear 
					in the window. You can then select an object there and tweak its position. When you 
					are done hit apply and the combo gets temporally saved until you hit "Save all" or 
					"Save - Save map".<br/>
					You can drag and drop combinations into the game window.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="usecode_edit">
			<header>Custom Usecode</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					As hinted at (see <extref doc="docs" target="terms"/>) Usecode is actually what runs Ultima 7
					and therefore any game created with <Studio/>.<br/>
					As of yet we do not have a Usecode editor/debugger. So writing your own Usecode is not 
					that easy.
				</para>
				<para>
					For an example of how Usecode may look like download our experimental patch for BG at
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/snapshots/patch.zip"/>.<br/>
					In that zip you'll find a readme.txt which tells you how to run it.<br/>
					You will also see two files called usecode.uc and usecode.
				</para>
				<para>
					Usecode.uc is the usecode script that will help you understand our usecode language.<br/>
					When you run ucc (see <ref target="tools"/>) with that file 
					(e.g. "ucc -o usecode usecode.uc") you will get the file called usecode. This file 
					'usecode' should be the same as the one in the zip file.
				</para>
				<para>
					Someone does have to write extensive documentation for this but I (Dominus) am not
					really up for that task.<br/>
					Pertex has written some documentation at <extref target="http://www.sophen.de/exult/"/>
					that might be able help you.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Egg editing">
		<sub name="eggs_explained">
			<header>Explaining eggs</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					An egg in its simplest form is an object that is placed in the world, but is 
					invisible to a normal user. When the player meets the requirements of an egg, 
					it causes the egg to become activated. Eggs can activate anything from monster 
					spawns, to changes in the current music, to the activation of custom usecode. You 
					may want to place the eggs in map-editing mode because eggs don't activate in this 
					mode. Then switch off map-editing mode to test how your egg will work during game 
					play.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="eggs_type">
			<header>The different types of eggs</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Currently <Studio/> supports the following types of eggs (more details follow):
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Monster</strong>(spawning)<br/>
						allows for the creation of a creature when certain conditions are met, usually
						when your character gets within a certain distance of the egg.
						It also allows for the creation of simple objects like walls or furniture to 
						appear when the Avatar gets near. This could make for some interesting effects.</li>
					<li><strong>Jukebox</strong><br/>
						sets the background music when the character enters a certain area.</li>
					<li><strong>Sound Effect</strong>and <strong>Voice</strong><br/>
						will play a selected sound or voice when the character meets the required values 
						set in the egg creation menu.</li>
					<li><strong>Usecode</strong><br/>
						allows for the activation of custom usecode when an egg's requirements are met. 
						The creation of custom usecode is discussed (though not in depth) at 
						<ref target="usecode_edit"/>.</li>
					<li><strong>Missile</strong><br/>
						create interesting objects like flamethrower traps.</li>
					<li><strong>Teleport</strong><br/>
						transportthe avatar anywhere on the map when certain conditions are met.</li>
					<li><strong>Weather</strong><br/>
						temporarily set the in-game weather.</li>
					<li><strong>Path</strong><br/>
						set the destination of a teleport egg to a specific object.</li>
					<li><strong>Button</strong><br/>
						is used to activate eggs in the vicinity that are set to external</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="place_eggs">
			<header>Add, remove and edit eggs</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The most convenient way to create an egg is to select <strong>Create new egg</strong>
					from the edit menu. This will pop up the <strong>Exult Egg</strong> window. Here you 
					can select the type of egg you wish to create and the properties you are going to 
					give it. When you are happy with the egg press <strong>apply</strong> and then enter 
					<Exult/> and place the egg wherever you like. To remove an egg, select it while in 
					map-edit mode and press <key>ctrl+x</key> to cut the egg. ou can still paste it 
					elsewhere if you like. To edit an egg, double click it in map editing mode. This 
					will bring up the egg window where you will be able to change an existing egg's 
					attributes.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="eggs_properties">
			<header>Properties of eggs</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Before you select the type of egg you want you can edit basic properties of eggs.
					These are:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Probability</strong><br/> 
						of the egg being activated. By giving an egg a probability of 100 you can ensure 
						that whenever the requirements necessary to make an egg activate are met, the egg 
						will activate. With a probability of 0 nothing will ever happen when the egg's 
						requirements are met. A probability anywhere between 0 and 100 will cause the 
						activation of an egg to be a random event.</li>
					<li><strong>Distance</strong><br/>
						allows you to set how far a character needs to be from an egg in order to activate
						it. Each distance unit is equal to one tile (8x8 pixel) of the map.</li>
					<li><strong>Criteria</strong><br/>
						is very important as it sets what needs to be done to activate the egg. The 
						options are:<br/>
						<strong>Cached in</strong> - An egg with this characteristic is activated when 
						the chunk it is on is loaded into memory. This usually happens from several screens 
						away.<br/>
						<strong>Party near</strong> - causes an egg to be activated whenever the player 
						controlled character or any of his party members wander within the area specified 
						by the distance option.<br/>
						<strong>Avatar near</strong> - exactly the same as party near except only registers 
						where the main character is moved, ignoring actions by the party members.<br/>
						<strong>Avatar far</strong> - Its like Avatar near except with a twist. This 
						property allows you to walk into the area specified by the distance property but then 
						as you leave the area the egg will be activated as you distance yourself from it. 
						Can be great for sneak attacks from behind.<br/>
						<strong>Avatar footpad</strong> - In this case the distance property is ignored and 
						the Avatar has to physically step onto the egg.<br/>
						<strong>Party footpad</strong> - This option is identical to the Avatar footpad option 
						except if either the main character or one of his companions stumbles onto the egg it 
						will be activated.<br/>
						<strong>Something on</strong> - This egg is activated whenever an object is placed 
						within the area specified by an egg.<br/>
						<strong>External</strong> - Eggs set to the external characteristic will be activated 
						by button eggs in the vicinity.
						</li>
					<li><strong>Flag</strong><br/>
						final attribute you can give an egg to determine whether it will be activated or not. 
						As a note you can mix and match flags, you can set an egg to nocturnal once only or 
						nocturnal auto-reset.<br/>
					 	<strong>Nocturnal</strong> - Any egg with this setting will only be activated during 
					 	the nighttime. Great for setting the spawning of creatures of the night, or giving 
					 	some nice night time music.<br/>
						<strong>Hatched</strong> - This creates an egg that has already been activated. It 
						is inactive and will not do anything.<br/>
						<strong>Once-Only</strong> - Any egg with this flag applied will only hatch once and 
						then disappear from the game world.<br/>
						<strong>Auto-reset</strong> - Eggs with this flag attached will continue to activate 
						every time the conditions set in the egg menu are met.</li>
				</ul>				
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="place_monsters">
			<header>Placing a monster spawning egg</header>
			<body>				
				<para>
					The first thing you want to consider before placing monster spawn is some of the basic egg 
					attributes. What probability do you want? What distance? Will it be a nocturnal creature?
					Next you have to set the monster specific egg attributes. The first question is probably 
					what type of monster you want to place. You can now switch to the main <Studio/> window, 
					select shapes.vga and choose a shape. Drag and drop this on the "Exult Egg" window. Frame # 
					isn't overly important when placing a monster, but for placing an object it can be very 
					important. Enter these attributes into their respective form. You next have to set the 
					monster's schedule. The various schedules that are important for a monster spawn are 
					discussed next. You also have to set the spawned monster's alignment.<br/>
					Any creature set to a neutral alignment will ignore the Avatar and friends, following their 
					schedule until attacked. Any creature set to hostile will immediately attack the Avatar if 
					you get too close. Using the friendly alignment naturally evil creatures such as ethereal 
					monsters will still attack, but good or neutral characters such as stone golems will continue 
					out their assigned schedule if given the friendly alignment.<br/>
					As a final monster spawn option, you can set the number of creatures you want to appear using 
					the count option. You can set anywhere from 1 to 31 monsters. When you're finished setting 
					the egg how you want, simply press "Apply" and place the egg on the world map.<br/>
					<img alt="Exult Egg window" src="images/studio3.jpg"/><br/>					
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="creature_schedules">
			<header>Schedules of Creatures</header>
			<body>				
				<para>
					When setting a monster spawn you will most like want to use one of the following schedules.
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Horiz. Pace</strong><br/>
						Any creature given this schedule will pace back and forth in a horizontal manner. Great 
						for guards and sentries</li>
					<li><strong>Vert. Pace</strong><br/>
						Same as the horizontal pace, except in a vertical direction.</li>
					<li><strong>Hound</strong><br/>
						Any creature given this schedule will slowly follow the main character wherever he goes.
						Good for creatures that won't take no for an answer.</li>
					<li><strong>Stand</strong><br/>
						Creatures given this setting will stand in one place until given a better reason to move.</li>
					<li><strong>Loiter</strong><br/>
						Creatures given this setting will wander aimlessly. They will move in random directions 
						a bit at a time.</li>
					<li><strong>Wander</strong><br/>
						Any creature given this setting will slowly move around a fairly large area.</li>
					<li><strong>Wait</strong><br/>
						Creatures given this setting will complacently stay in one place.</li>
					<li><strong>Shy</strong><br/>
						Creatures given this setting are afraid of the main character and will slowly wander away 
						from the Avatar.</li>
					<li><strong>Waiter</strong><br/>
						Give a creature this schedule and watch him run back and forth around a crowded area like 
						he has a purpose.</li>
					<li><strong>Graze</strong><br/>
						An awful lot like loiter except the character seems to stay a little more to one area.</li>
					<li><strong>Duel</strong><br/>
						Doesn't do a whole lot by itself, but put two neutral creatures with these settings 
						beside each other and its rumble time. This also works by placing them near training 
						dummies or archery targets. For an extra laugh place 10 spawns each set for 31 guards 
						to appear in duelling mode.</li>
					<li><strong>Patrol</strong><br/>
						A creature given this setting will very slowly wander from place to place.<br/>
						<img alt="Guards duel" src="images/studio4.jpg"/><br/></li>					
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="audio_eggs">
			<header>Jukebox, Sound Effects and Voice eggs</header>
			<body>				
				<para>
					Using these eggs couldn't be more straightforward, select the sound effect, music score, 
					or recorded digital voice you desire and then place them onto the map. When a character 
					activates the egg they begin to play. You can set music and sound effects to play on a 
					continuous loop for continuous effects such as water fountains or short pieces of 
					background music that you don't want to quit until a new music egg is triggered.<br/>
					In the game window you can test and find out the # of the audio by pressing 
					<key>Alt+1</key>.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="usecode_eggs">
			<header>Usecode eggs</header>
			<body>				
				<para>
					Usecode eggs have many different functions that will be discussed later. The important 
					thing to remember about the usecode egg menu is that function number is where you insert 
					the hex value of the usecode function that this egg is going to execute.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="missile_eggs">
			<header>Missile eggs</header>
			<body>				
				<para>
					When you place a missile egg, the first thing you have to set is the egg's activation 
					attributes. Do you want an egg to activate when the Avatar is near a certain spot, or should 
					someone have to directly step on the trap?<br/>
					To choose the type of missile you want to shoot from your trap, select shape number 1 for a 
					fireball that doesn't do damage, 3 for a lightning bolt, and 6 to shoot arrows. Select shape 
					9 for a fireball that actually does damage. You can also set the direction you want the trap 
					to fire when it is activated, you can choose any of the 8 cardinal directions.<br/>
					You can also use the delay timer to set how steady you want the stream of projectiles to be. 
					1 makes a constant stream of projectiles, while a value of 10 makes for the occasional danger. 
					Don't set the timer to 0 seconds, <Exult/> REALLY doesn't like this.<br/>
					Using these options you can make some pretty dangerous obstacles for the Avatar to avoid.
				</para>
				<para>
					<strong>Note:</strong> Shape numbers assume you are using either BG or SI data. When making 
					a new game you can set weapons info of shapes yourself and choose which shape numbers are 
					used by each weapon.<br/>
					<img alt="missiles" src="images/studio5.jpg"/><br/>
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="teleport_eggs">
			<header>Teleport eggs</header>
			<body>				
				<para>
					The primary purpose of the teleport egg is to simply move a character from one place to another 
					instantly without forcing them to walk there. Think of any dungeon teleporter that moves you 
					from one place to another.<br/>
					The teleport egg has two primary modes. The first mode possessed by the teleport egg is to 
					choose the location that the party will be warped to by specifying a location on the over world 
					map using x and y co-ordinates. If you place an egg on the map and a character meets the 
					criteria specified by the egg they will be whisked away to the x and y coordinates set by the 
					egg. This option can't be used to move your character onto roofs because there is no z option 
					provided.<br/>
					To switch to the other mode of teleporting, press the use coordinates button.
					This directs the teleported towards a numbered path egg. By giving a path egg a unique number 
					and then placing it on the map any teleporter set to this egg will transport the player there.
					The advantage of teleporting using a path egg is you can teleport your character onto the second 
					floor of a building if the path egg is placed up there.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="weather_eggs">
			<header>Weather eggs</header>
			<body>				
				<para>
					There are two attributes of the weather egg that one needs to worry about.
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>Weather</strong><br/>
						The most important attribute as this sets the effect you can expect when an egg 
						is activated.<br/>
						<strong>Halt</strong> - Halts and current weather and set the world to a pleasant sunny 
						default.<br/>
						<strong>Storm</strong> - Lots of thunder and lightning and the world darkens.<br/>
						<strong>Cloudy</strong> - Some rain, not a lot else going on<br/>
						<strong>Magic storm</strong> - Lots of thunder and lightning and the world darkens. As 
						well this type of storm eliminates the character's magic casting abilities while the 
						storm is in affect.</li>
					<li><strong>Duration</strong><br/>
						sets the how long the chosen weather will last. The time is measured in game time and can
						last up to 255 minutes.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="path_eggs">
			<header>Path eggs</header>
			<body>				
				<para>
					The path egg is useful for placing an individual teleport location by hand. Give the path egg 
					a unique number and then direct a teleport egg towards it. If the person steps on a teleporter 
					set to the same number as the path egg, they will be teleported there.<br/>
					Note that it only works up to a distance of 256 tiles in each direction (in a square, not a 
					circle). It also doesn't world-wrap, meaning  a teleport egg at the far east edge won't find 
					a path egg at the far west edge.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="button_eggs">
			<header>Button eggs</header>
			<body>				
				<para>
					The button egg has the interesting ability to activate all eggs in the immediate vicinity that 
					are set to external. You can set the area around the egg that will be affected by increasing 
					the distance setting, keeping in mind that each distance setting is equal to 1 tile (8x8 pixel).
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="NPC editing">
		<sub name="npc_edit">
			<header>How to edit an NPC</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Sorry to disappoint but this section is not yet done...
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Basic map editing">
		<sub name="learn_edit">
			<header>Learning the basics of map editing</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The first thing one will probably want to do once they have <Studio/> running is to begin 
					creating their own little world. The first step towards this is learning how to move objects 
					and chunks, and placing items from <Studio/> into the game world. And the best way to 
					learn is by using an existing game like BG or SI.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="move_obj">
			<header>Moving objects around</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Perhaps the simplest way of making your world truly unique is to start out by moving existing 
					structures around. Move is the default option in <Studio/>, but to ensure you are in move 
					mode select it from the mode menu. You know you are in map-editing mode when a red grid is 
					highlighted across the world. You can select any object (notice the red highlighting of 
					selected objects) with the mouse and move it around. This works using a simple drag and drop 
					approach. Simply grab a tree with a right click and place it on the other side of your viewing 
					area. The only thing you can't drag and drop are chucks, which are the large ground sections 
					mapped by the red grid system. If you want to place one object on top of another, just drag it 
					on top and release. If the object can be supported in that position it will stay there. For a 
					brief guide on placing an object that won't have support, but will be floating see further down.
					You can also change an object's x and y coordinates by selecting the object and pressing 
					<key>ctrl+arrow keys</key>. An object's z coordinate can be changed by selecting the object and 
					pressing <key>ctrl+page up</key> or <key>ctrl+page down</key>.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="place_obj">
			<header>How to place objects from Exult Studio</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					This could not be simpler in <Studio/>. Simply select a shape from the shapes.vga menu and 
					drag it into <Exult/>. In Windows I personally prefer to drag the item onto the taskbar, hovering 
					over the <Exult/> window, wait for the window to switch and then place the item. You will get a 
					green grid that will show you exactly where you can expect the object to show up. Once you 
					found where you would like the object to appear, simply let go of the mouse and the object is 
					placed. If you're unhappy where you placed the object, simply drag and drop it somewhere else.<br/>
					<img alt="green grid" src="images/studio6.jpg"/>
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="control_obj">
			<header>Mark, delete, copy, make multiple objects</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					To mark multiple objects hold down <key>ctrl</key> and click on the objects you want to mark.
					This is very useful when you want to handle a whole bunch of objects (like deleting, copying 
					or multiplying objects).
				</para>
				<para>
					If you placed an object onto the world map that you now feel should be removed, select the 
					object with your mouse and press <key>ctrl+x</key> or select the cut option from the <Studio/> 
					Menu.<br/> 
					This will remove the object from the world and place it into memory (if you don't want to keep 
					the object in memory simply press <key>del</key> when it is selected). If you want to the object 
					somewhere else, press <key>ctrl+v</key> or select the paste option, this will create a set of 
					crosshairs that you can use to place your new object. To create multiple copies of an object, 
					select an object so it has a red outline and press <key>ctrl+c</key> or select the copy option. 
					You can now paste another copy of the object on the world using paste.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="float_obj">
			<header>Making floating objects like bridges</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					So you want to create an unsupported section of balcony, or you want to make it look like that 
					Kilrathi ship you just placed is actually hovering above the ground. To do this set the 
					object's z height by changing the value in the grid height menu. If you want your character to 
					be able to walk underneath an object it must be set 4 grid heights above the surface which your 
					character is walking on. If you want your character to be able to walk on an object, the top of 
					the object must be no more then 1-grid height above the surface the character is currently on.<br/>
					<img alt="crate bridge" src="images/studio7.jpg"/>
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="change_frame">
			<header>How to change the frame of an object</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					So you see an apple tree on the map, but you think you'd much rather have a palm tree. <Studio/> 
					supports many different frames for each object. To change the frame of an object, select an 
					object so it highlights red and select the "Basic Properties" option. The <Exult/> Object box 
					should appear. This gives you the option to select a different frame for the object to see what 
					other frames this particular object has. The <Exult/> Object option also allows you to manually set 
					the height of an object that already exists on the map. Another way to select an objects frame, 
					is to select the object from the shapes menu and then using the frames option in the lower right 
					hand corner select just the frame you're looking for. Then you can then drag the object into your 
					world normally.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="change_chunks">
			<header>How to change chunks (the big red outlined square)</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					To change the large pieces of map that are sandwiched between the red lines of the map-editing 
					grid you have to place a chunk, instead of a shape. The various chunks available in <Studio/> 
					are located under the heading U7chunks. The chunks are many large pieces of preformed landscape 
					that help give the world a more consistent feel. They also make the job of editing the world 
					somewhat easier. To place a chunk simply place it the same way that you would a shape, but keep 
					in mind that chunks can only be placed within the red squared formed by the map-editing grid.<br/>
					<img alt="chunk placing" src="images/studio8.jpg"/>
				</para>
				<para>
					There are a lot of interesting chunks already available in the chunks.vga file, but what if you 
					want to make some minor changes to the design of a pre-made chunk? Maybe make the Britannia 
					transport system a little more safe by painting a yellow line down the centre of each road chunk.
					By selecting the Edit terrain option you can change a chunk by placing objects directly onto a 
					chunk, doing this permanently changes the chunk you are editing so be careful. It may not look it, 
					but if you then select the chunk you edited from the chunks.vga menu the chunk you place will 
					have the changes you made. Also be careful because when you edit a chunk you change every chunk 
					in the game that is the same as the chunk you're editing. To solve this problem go into the chunks 
					menu and right click the chunk you want to edit and select new, then duplicate. You now have two 
					identical chunks. You can then place your new chunk onto the world and edit it how you like 
					without editing the other chunks. You can now place this duplicate chunk wherever you like and 
					it will have the changes you made.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="multi_obj">
			<header>How to make a structures consisting of multiple objects</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Many structures present in <Exult/> consist of multiple objects. Examples of these are roofs, 
					long sections of wall or fence. Constructing a roof can be a long and difficult process 
					because it involves properly positioning multiple small objects and then manually setting 
					each object's height. That's where the New Combos option located in the Tools menu comes in 
					handy. Select the New Combos option and then enter the window where Exult is running. Your 
					mouse will have become a cross hair. Double click on all the objects you plan on adding to 
					your new object. In this example we're making a roof by double-clicking all sections of the 
					roof.<br/>
					<img alt="combo builder" src="images/studio9.jpg"/>
				</para>
				<para>
					As you double-click each object, the selection appears in the combo window showing you exactly 
					what you have selected. Now give the object a name and select Okay. The object will now be 
					temporarily saved in the combos.flx menu. The object can now be placed on the map normally. If 
					you make a combo you want to keep, make sure to save before quitting <Studio/>. You can 
					continue editing your combos even after you originally finish them, by double right clicking 
					them from the combo menu.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="other_combo">
			<header>More things you can do with Combos</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					One problem with the <Studio/> combo option is that when the combo is created many of the 
					items are not in the rendering order you would want them to appear in game. To fix this problem, 
					you can select individual items in the combo-builder window and by changing their viewing order 
					you can make sure that all items appear exactly how you want them. You can also use the x,y,z 
					coordinates to move individual items in your combo around to make sure that your combo looks 
					exactly how you want. If you added an object to your combo that you don't wish to keep, simply 
					select the item from the combo menu and press remove.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="paint_forest">
			<header>Use the paint feature to quickly create a forest</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The best way to create multiple objects fast and conveniently is to use the paint option. If 
					you want to make a forest of trees fast, select the tree from the shapes menu and then select 
					the paint option from the mode menu. Select the <Exult/> window and you can now quickly place 
					multiple objects with the green grid. 
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
	<section title="Miscellaneous">
		<sub name="tools">
			<header>Other tools that might be useful</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					In the process of creating <Exult/> the team came up with some useful 
					tools that might help in editing/making a game.<br/>
					These can be built from the <Exult/> source or you can download
					the Windows binary snapshot. The source and binary snapshot can be found at
					<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/download.php"/>.<br/>
					The tools are:
				</para>
				<ul>
					<li><strong>expack</strong>:<br/>
						lets you extract and create Flex files. 
						See the 
						<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/expack.txt">manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>ipack</strong>:<br/>
						a tool for creating and updating <Exult/> and U7 image archives, such as 'shapes.vga'. 
						See the 
						<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/ipack.txt">manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>shp2pcx</strong>:<br/>
						converts all frames contained in a Shape file into PCX-format image files. 
						See the 
						<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/shp2pcx.txt">manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>splitshp</strong>:<br/>
						can be used to combine frames of a Shape file into one file, or split a Shape 
						file into its component frames. 
						See the 
						<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/splitshp.txt">manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>textpack</strong>:<br/>
						can be used edit text flex files. 
						See <extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/textpack.txt">manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>ucc</strong>:<br/>
						can be used to create custom usecode (see <ref target="usecode_edit"/>).<br/>
						See the 
						<extref target="http://exult.sourceforge.net/ucc.txt">manual</extref>.</li>
					<li><strong>The GIMP Plug-in</strong>:<br/>
						can be used for editing shapes in the GIMP. Handles multiframe Shape files. 
						See <extref target="http://www.gimp.org"/> for information on the GIMP.</li>
					<li><strong>Photoshop Plug-in</strong>:<br/>
						can be used for editing shapes in Photoshop. Can't handle multiframe Shape files. And 
						also can't handle indexed images with Alpha correctly.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="port_platforms">
			<header>Porting <Studio/> to other platforms</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					Currently <Studio/> runs on U*ix and Windows platforms. First it only
					ran on U*ix but with some effort by Colourless, Kirben and Mark Siewart
					it was successfully ported to Win32.
				</para>
				<para>
					A port to other platforms depends on when someone volunteers to do the work :-)
					There are three issues:
				</para>
				<ul>
   				<li>GTK has to be ported to the platform.</li>
   				<li><Studio/> uses sockets to communicate with <Exult/>.</li>
   				<li>X drag-n-drop is used to put new objects on the landscape. The
					'drop' part of this had to be rewritten for Win32 <Exult/>, OR,
					drag-n-drop could be an enhancement to SDL someday.<br/>
					As an alternative to dragging objects, you can now select a shape,
					then insert it into the game window by left-clicking while holding the
					Shift key down.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>	
		<sub name="client_server_stuff">
			<header>About this client/server stuff?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					A map-editor needs to provide the ability to display the game, place
					objects on the map, and move objects around. That functionality is already in
					<Exult/>, and it makes sense to reuse it. So we could have made <Exult/> a part of
					<Studio/>. However, <Exult/> is already a huge program, and is getting
					unwieldy to work on.
				</para>
				<para>
					With this architecture, <Studio/> can have all the messy code for
					displaying/editing dialog boxes, while <Exult/> only needs a little bit
					of work to handle requests.
				</para>
				<para>
					Also, I (Jeff) wanted to get a little experience programming with
					sockets:-)
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="terrain_stuff">
			<header>About this 'terrain-editing' stuff and why you can't just
  					drag objects to where you want.</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					This confused me too, and I originally planned on doing away with it.
					But do a little arithmetic:  U7's world has 3072x3072 tiles; that's
					over 9 million that need to be set. My guess is that they came up
					with the idea behind 'u7chunks' to save artists time and to give the
					map a consistent look.
				</para>
				<para>
					The basic idea is that each 'chunk' of flat terrain, 16x16 tiles, is
					stored in 'u7chunks', and is indexed by its position in this file (0,
					1, 2, ...). The 'u7map' file specifies, for each 'chunk' in the U7
					map, which of the terrains is to be used. Since the entire map has
					192x192 chunks, or a total of 36,864, and since 'u7chunks' has 3072
					entries, each terrain is shared an average of over 10 times. When you
					go into map-editing mode in Exult, the numbers displayed are the
					indices from 'u7chunks'.
				</para>
				<para>
					So here are the three sorts of scenery that you can see and edit:
				</para>
				<ol>
					<li>The 'terrain' (flat landscape, rocks, shrubs, and first-story
    					buildings) specified in 'u7chunks' and 'u7map'.</li>
    				<li>Other non-moveable objects (second-floor structures, trees) specified in
    					the 'ifixnn' files.</li>
    				<li>Moveable and changeable objects specified in the 'iregnn' files.</li>
				</ol>
				<para>
					The challenge of writing a map-editor is keeping the above straight,
					and reading/storing from/to the correct files. It's sorta-kinda
					working now :-)
				</para>
				<para>
					For a more detailed explanation, see Gary Thompson's paper,
					'u7edit.txt' in our 'docs' directory.
				</para>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="what_next">
			<header>What's next?</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					The next things to be implemented are:
				</para>
				<ul>
				<li><Studio/> needs to be able to automatically create palettes 1-n from palette 0 
					using the code from ipack.</li>
				<li>It will also be very nice to have a Usecode debugger someday as well 
					(Willem is actually working on it).</li>
   				<li>A 'flags' editor for viewing and editing the global Usecode flags by name.</li>
				<li>A 'barge' editor for creating things like ships and carts.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
		<sub name="win32_bugs">
			<header>Known Bugs with the Win32 port</header>
			<body>
				<para>
					<Studio/> is of course far from perfect and the Win32 port still has some bugs:
				</para>
				<ul>
				<li>Windows NT4 and Windows 2k don't work at the moment as there is some strange
					connection problem between <Exult/> and <Studio/>. We have not yet been able
					to figure out the problem.</li>
				<li>If you start <Studio/> from an SI game <Studio/> defaults to the BG data files.
					You have to change the game dir manually from the files menu.</li>
   				<li>When you change the game directory you can't select a different drive than the one
   					<Studio/> is running from.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
  	<section title="Credits">
		<sub name="thanks">
			<header>Thanks</header>
			<body>
				<ul>
					<li>Colourless, Kirben and Mark Siewart invested a lot of effort to port
					<Studio/> to Win32.</li>
				</ul>
			</body>
		</sub>
	</section>
</studiodoc>